<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hereafter foloweth a compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth made in Mou[n]tpyllier, compyled by Andrew Boorde of physiycke doctour, dedycated to the armypotent prynce, and valyaunt Lorde Thomas Duke of Northfolche.</title>
            <title>Compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth</title>
            <author>Boorde, Andrew, 1490?-1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1542</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3378.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851539</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1656:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hereafter foloweth a compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth made in Mou[n]tpyllier, compyled by Andrew Boorde of physiycke doctour, dedycated to the armypotent prynce, and valyaunt Lorde Thomas Duke of Northfolche.</title>
                  <title>Compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth</title>
                  <author>Boorde, Andrew, 1490?-1549.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge in seynt Martyns parysshe besyde charynge Crosse, at the sygne of seynt Iohn Euangelyste. for Iohn Gowghe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1542]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication is dated 5 May 1547.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-N⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:1"/>
            <p>¶ Hereafter folo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth a compendyous Regy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or a dyetary of Helth, made in Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tpyllier, compyled by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Boorde of Phyſycke doctour, dedycated to the armypotent Prynce, and valyaunt Lorde Thomas Duke of Northfolche.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Galyen prynce, of Phyſycke.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:3"/>
            <head>¶ The preface. ¶ To the precelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and army potent prynce, lorde Thomas duke of Northfolch, Andrew Borde of Phyſycke doctour doth ſurrender humyle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacyon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmoch as it pleaſed your grace to ſend for me (to ſyr Robert Drewry knyght) whiche was the yeare in the whiche lorde Thomas cardynal biſhop of york was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to go to his ſee of york to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll in Phyſycke in certayne vrgent cauſes, requyryng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauyte of your body, at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme I beyng but a yon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge doctour in my ſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or faculte, durſt not to preſume to mynyſter any medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone to you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the counceyl of may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter doctour Butte, whiche had a longe continuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with you &amp; a great cognyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:3"/> not onely of your infyrmyte, but alſo of your complexyon &amp; dyet. But he not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to your grace, thankes be to God, your grace recuperatyng your helth. And conuocated thorowe the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges goodnes to wayte on his prepotent mageſte: I than dyd paſſe ouer the ſees agayne. And dyd go to all the vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyties and ſcoles approbated, and beyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge within the precinct of chryſtendome. And all was done for to haue a trewe cognyſcyon of the practis of Phyſycke, the whiche obtayned. I than cotydyally remembryng your bountyfull goodnes ſhewed to me, &amp; alſo beynge at the well hed of Phyſycke, dyd conſult with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny egregyous Doctours of Phyſycke / what matter I ſhuld wryte, the whiche myght be acceptable, and profitable for the ſauyte of your body. The ſayde doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours knowynge my trewe intencyon, dyd aduertyſe me to compyle and make ſome boke of dyete, the which not onely ſhuld do your grace pleaſure, but alſo it
<pb facs="tcp:16817:4"/> ſhuld be neceſſary &amp; profytable for your noble poſterite, &amp; for many other men the whiche wolde folowe the effycacyte of this boke / the whiche is called the Regyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or dietary of helth. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re that I do ſpeake in this boke but of dietes, and other thynges concernynge the ſame. If any man therfore wolde haue remedy for any ſyckenes or dyſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, let hym loke in a boke of my makyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, named y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Breuyare of helth. But yf it ſhall pleaſe your grace to loke on a boke, the which I dyd make in Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyller, named y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Introductory of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege, there ſhall you ſe many new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / the whiche I haue no doubte but that your grace wyl accept and lyke the boke, the whiche is a pryntynge beſyde ſaynt Dunſtons churche within Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple barre ouer agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Temple. And where I haue dedycated this boke to your grace, and haue not ornated and floryſſhed it with eloquent ſpeche and rethorycke termes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which in all wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges
<pb facs="tcp:16817:4"/> is vſed theſe modernall dayes, I do ſubmyt me to your bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyful good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. And alſo dyuers tymes in my wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynges I do wryte wordes of myrth / truely it is for no other intencyon / but to make your grace mery, for myrth is one of the chefeſt thynges of Phyſycke the which doth aduertyſe euery man to be mery, and to beware of pencyfulnes, truſtynge to your affluent goodneſſe to take no diſpleaſure with any contentes of this boke, but to accept my good wyl and dylygent labour. And furthermore I do truſt to your ſuperabundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyouſnes, that you wyll conſydre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue and zeale, the which I haue to your pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſperyte, and that I do it for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weele, the whiche I beſeche Ieſu chryſt longe to contynew to his wyll and plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure in this lyfe. And after this tranſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory lyfe remunerate you with celeſtyal ioy and eternall glorye.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Mount<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyllier. <date>The .v. day of May. The yere of our Lorde Ieſu Chryſte. M.v.C.xlij.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:5"/>
            <head>¶ Here foloweth the Table of the Chapytres.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe fyrſte Chapytre doth ſhewe where a man ſhuld cytuat or ſet his mancyon place or howſe, for the helth of his body.</item>
               <item>¶ The ſeconde Chapytre doth ſhewe a man howe he ſhulde buylde his howſe, and that the proſpect be good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſeruacion of helth.</item>
               <item>¶ The thyrde Chapitre doth ſhewe a man to buylde his howſe in a pure and freſſhe ayre for to lengthen his lyfe.</item>
               <item>¶ The .iiii. Chapytre doth ſhewe vnder what maner a man ſhuld buylde his howſe or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon in eſchewynge thynges that ſhuld ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his lyfe.</item>
               <item>¶ The .v. Chapytre doth ſhewe howe a man ſhuld ordre his howſe concernyng the imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to comforte the ſpyrytes of man.</item>
               <item>¶ The .vi. Chapytre doth ſhewe a man howe he ſhulde ordre his howſe and howſholde, and to lyue in quyetnes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .vii. Chapytre doth ſhew howe the hed of a howſe, or a howſeholder ſhulde exercyſe hym ſelfe for the helth of the ſoule and body.</item>
               <item>¶ The .viii. Chapytre doth ſhew howe a man ſhulde order hym ſelfe in ſlepynge, and wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:5"/> and in his apparell werynge.</item>
               <item>¶ The .ix. Chapitre doth ſhew that replecion or ſurfetynge doth moche harme to nature, and that abſtynence is the chyfeſt medyſon of all medyſons.</item>
               <item>¶ The .x. Chapytre treateth of all maner of drynkes, as of water, of wyne, of ale, of bere, of cyder, of meade, of metheglyn, &amp; of whay.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xi. Chapytre treateth of breade.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xii. Chapytre of potage, of ſewe, of ſtew pottes, of grewell, of fyrmente, of peaſe potage, of almon mylke, of ryce potage, of cawdels, of culleſes, of alebrues, of hony ſop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, and of all other maner of brothes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xiii. Chapitre treateth of whyt meate as of egges, butter, cheſe, mylke, crayme, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettes, of almon butter, and of beane butter.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xiiii. Chapytre treateth of fyſſhe.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xv. Chapytre treateth of wyld fowle, of tame fowle, and of byrdes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xvi. Chapytre treateth of fleſſhe, wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and domeſtycall.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xvii. Chapytre treateth of partyculer thynges of fyſſhe and fleſſhe.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xviii. Chapitre treateth of roſt meate of fryde meate, of ſoden or boyled meate, of bruled meate and of baken meate.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:6"/>
               <item>¶ The .xix. Chapytre treateth of rootes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xx. Chapytre treateth of certayne vſuall herbes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxi. Chapytre treateth of fruytes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxii. Chapytre treateth of ſpyces.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxiii. Chapytre ſheweth a dyate for ſanguyne men.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxiiii. Chapytre ſheweth a dyate for flematycke men.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxv. Chapytre ſheweth a dyate for colorycke men.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxvi. Chapytre doth ſhewe a dyate for melancoly men.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxvii. Chapytre treateth of a dyate and of an order to be vſed in the peſtyferous tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtilence &amp; the ſwetyng ſyckenes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxviii. Chapytre treateth of a dyate for them the whiche be in an agew or a feuer.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxix. Chapitre treateth of a dyate for them the whiche haue the Ilyacke, or the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycke and the ſtone.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxx. Chapytre treateth of a dyate for theym the whiche haue any of the kyndes of the gowtes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxi. Chapitre treateth of a dyate for them the which haue any kyndes of lepored.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxii. Chapytre treateth of a dyate
<pb facs="tcp:16817:6"/> for theym the whiche haue any of the kyndes of the fallynge ſyckenes.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxiii. Chapytre treateth of a dyate for them whiche haue any payne in theyr hed.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxiiii. Chapytre treateth of a dyate for them the whiche be in a conſumpcyon.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxv. Chapytre treateth of a dyate for them the which be aſmatycke men, beynge ſhort wynded or lackynge breath.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxvi. Chapytre doth ſhewe a dyate for them the whiche hath the palſy.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxvii. Chapitre doth ſhew an order &amp; a dyate for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be mad &amp; out of their wyt.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxviii. Chapytre treateth of a dyate for them which haue any kynde of the dropſy</item>
               <item>¶ The .xxxix. Chapytre treateth of a general dyate for all maner of men or women beyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſycke or whole.</item>
               <item>¶ The .xl. Chapytre doth ſhew an order or a faſſhyon, howe a ſycke man ſhall be ordered in his ſyckenes. And how a ſycke man ſhuld be vſed that is lykly to dye.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>¶ Here foloweth the dyetary or the regyment of helth.</head>
            <div type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>GALIEN PRYNCE OF PHISYCKE.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:7"/>
               <head>¶ The fyrſt Chapytre doth ſhew whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a man ſhulde cytuate or ſette his mancyon place or howſe for the health of his body.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat man of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour or worſhyp, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſtate, the whiche doth pretende to buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a howſe or any man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon place to inhabyte hym ſelfe. Or elles doth pretende to alter his howſe, or to alter olde buyldyng in to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyous and pleaſaunt buyldynge, not onely for his owne proper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite, welth, &amp; helth, but alſo for other men the whiche wyll reſort to hym: hauyng alſo a reſpect to his poſterite. ¶ Fyrſte it is neceſſarye and expedyent for hym to take hede, what counceyll God dyd gyue to Abraham, and after that to take hede what counceyll God dyd gyue to Moyſes, and to the chyldren of Iſraell, as it appereth in the .xiii chapytre of Exodi. and the .xx. cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pytre of Numeri, &amp; the .vi. chapytre of Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronomii. And alſo in the boke of Leuites, ſaying fyrſte to Abraham. Go thou forth of
<pb facs="tcp:16817:8"/> thy countre &amp; from thy cognacion or kynred. And come thou in to the countrey the whiche I wyll ſhew to the a countrey abundynge or plentyfull of mylke and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny. ¶ Here is to be noted that where there is plenty of mylke there is plenty of paſture, and no ſkarſyte of water, &amp; where there is plenty of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny there is no ſkarſyte but plentyfulneſſe of woddes, for there be mo bees in woddes, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quently abundaunce of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, than there be bees, or hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, or waxe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyues in gardyns or orchardes, wherfore it appereth that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer wyl buylde a mancyon place or a houſe, he muſt cytuat and ſet it there where he muſt be ſure to haue both water and woode, except for pleaſure he wyll buylde a howſe in or by ſome cytie or great towne the whiche be not deſtitude of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytes. But he the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyll dwell at pleaſure, and for proffyte, and helth of his body he muſt dwell at elbowe rome hauyng water and woode anexed to his place or howſe, for yf he be deſtytuted of any of the pryncypalles, that is to ſay fyrſt of wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for to waſſhe and to wrynge, to bake and to brewe, and dyuers other cauſes ſpecyally for parrell the whiche myght fall by fyre were a great dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous thynge. And better it
<pb facs="tcp:16817:8"/> were to lacke woode than to lacke water the premyſſes conſydered, althoughe that woode is a neceſſarye thynge, not onely for fewell, but alſo for other vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſes, ſpecyally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge buyldynge and teperacyons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ſeconde Chapytre doth ſhewe a man, howe he ſhuld buylde his houſe or manſyon, that the proſpect be fayre &amp; good for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacyon of helth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that a man haue choſen a conuenyent ſoyle and place accordynge to his mynde and purpoſe to buylde his howſe or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon on, he muſt haue afore caſt in his mynde, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proſpect to and fro the place be pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, fayre, and good to the eye, to beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woodes, the waters, the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the vales, the hylles, &amp; the playne grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And that euery thynge be deſent and fayre to the eye, not onely within the precyncte of the place appoynted to buylde a manſyon or a howſe to ſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities aboute it, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it may be placable to the eyes of all men to
<pb facs="tcp:16817:9"/> ſe &amp; to beholde whan they be a good dyſtaunt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of from the place, that it do ſtande co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyouſly. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous buyldyng of a place doth not onely ſatyſfye the mynde of the inhabytour, but alſo it doth comforte and reioyſeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes herte to ſe it, ſpecyally the pulcruſe proſpect. For my conſayte is ſuche that I had rather not to buyld a manſyon or a howſe, than to buylde one without a good reſpecte in it, to it, &amp; from it. For and the eye be not ſatyſfyed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde can not be conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted. And the mynde can not be contented the herte can not be pleaſed, yf the herte &amp; mynde be not pleaſed, nature doth abhorre. And yf nature do abhorre, mortyfycacyon of the vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and anymall, and ſpyrytuall powers do conſequently folowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The thyrde Chapytre doth ſhewe a man to buylde his howſe in a pure &amp; a freſſhe ayre to lengthen his lyfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothynge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept poyſon that doth putryfye or doth corrupt the blode of man and alſo doth mortyfye the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes of man, as doth a corrupt and a conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyous
<pb facs="tcp:16817:9"/> ayre. For Galyen terapentice nono ſayeth, whyther we wyll or wyll not we muſt grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto euery man ayre, for without the ayre no man can lyue. The ayre can not be to clene and pure, conſyderynge it doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe vs rounde aboute, and we do receyue it in to vs, we can not be without it, for we lyue by it as the fyſſhe lyueth by the water. Good ayre therfore is to be prayſed. For yf the ayre be fryſke, pure, and clene about the manſyon or howſe it doth conſerue the lyfe of man, it doth comfort the brayne. And the powers na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall anymall and ſpyrytuall, ingendrynge and makynge good blode, in the whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth the lyfe of man. And contraryly euyl and corrupt ayres doth infecte the blode, and doth ingendre many corrupte humours, and doth putryfye the brayne, and doth corrupte the herte, &amp; therfore it doth brede many dyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſes &amp; infyrmytyes thorowe the which mans lyfe is abreuyated and ſhortned. Many thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges doth infect, putryfye, and corrupteth the ayre, as the influence of ſondry ſterres, and ſtandyng waters, ſtynkyng myſtes, and mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhes, caryn lyinge longe aboue the grounde, moche people in a ſmal rome lying vnclenly, and beyng fylthe and ſluttyſſhe, wherfore he
<pb facs="tcp:16817:10"/> that doth pretende to buylde his manſyon or houſe, he muſt prouyde that he do nat cytuat his howſe nyghe to any marſſhe or maryſſhe grownde, that there be nat nygh to the place ſtynkynge and putryfyed ſtandyng waters, pooles, pondes, nor myers, but at leſtwyſe that ſuch waters do ſtande vpon a ſtony or a grauayle grownde myxt with claye, and that ſome freſſhe ſprynge haue a recourſe to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe and to refreſſhe the ſayd ſtandyng wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Alſo there muſt be circumſpection had that there be not aboute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howſe or manſyon no ſtynkynge dyches, gutters, nor canelles, nor corrupt dunghylles, nor ſynkes, excepte they be oft and dyuers tymes mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyfyed and made clene. Swepyng of howſes and cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres ought nat to be done as long as any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man is within the precynct of the howſe, for the duſt doth putryfy the ayre makyng it dence. Alſo nygh to the place let nother flaxe nor hempe be watered, &amp; beware of the ſnoffe of candelles, and of the ſauour of apples for theſe thynges be contagyous and infectyue. Alſo myſty &amp; clowdy dayes, impetous and vehement wyndes, troublous and vaporous wether is nat good to labour in it to open the pores to let in infectious ayre. Furthermore
<pb facs="tcp:16817:10"/> beware of pyſſynge in drawghtes, &amp; permyt no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon pyſſyng place be aboute the howſe or manſyon, &amp; let the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon howſe of caſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be ouer ſome water, or elles elongated from the howſe. And beware of emptynge of pyſſe pottes and pyſſing in chymnes, ſo that all euyll and contagyous ayres may be expel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, and clene ayre kept vnputryfyed. And of all thynges let the buttery, the celler, the kyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen, the larder howſe, with all other howſes of offyces be kept clene, that there be no fylth in them, but good &amp; odyferous ſauours, and to expell &amp; expulſe all corrupt &amp; contagyous ayre, loke in the .xxvii. Chapytre of this boke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .iiij. Chapytre doth ſhew vnder what maner &amp; faſſhyon a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld buylde his howſe or manſyon, in exchewynge thynges that ſhortneth mans lyfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han a man doth begyn to bylde his hous or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyon place he muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyde (ſayth Ieſus chryſt) before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he begyn to buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for all thyngꝭ neceſſary for the performacyon of it, leſt that whan he
<pb facs="tcp:16817:11"/> hath made his fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion, &amp; can not fynyſſhe his worke that he hath begon, euery man wyl deryde hym ſaying. This man dyd begyn to buylde, but he can not fynyſſhe or make an end of his purpoſe, for a man muſt conſyder the exſpence before he do begynne to buylde, for there goeth to buyldynge many a nayle, many pynnes, many lathes, and many tyles or ſlates or ſtrawes, beſyde other greater char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, as tymbre, bordes, lyme, ſand, ſtones or brycke, beſyde the workmanſhyp and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementes. But a man the whiche haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd or hath in ſtore to accomplyſſhe his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and hath choſen a good ſoyle and place to cytuat his howſe or manſyon, and that the proſpecte be good, and that the ayre be pure, fryſke and clene. Then he that wyll buylde, let hym make his fundacyon vpon a graualy grownde myxt with clay, or els let hym buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vpon a roche of ſtone, or els vpon an hyll or a hylles ſyde. And ordre &amp; edyfy the howſe ſo that the pryncypall and chefe proſpectes may be Eeſt and weeſt, ſpecyally North eeſt, Sowth eeſt, and South weeſt, for the mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyal wynde of al wyndes is the moſte worſt, for the Southwynde doth corrupt and doth make euyl vapours. The Eeſt wynde is tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perate,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:11"/> fryſke, and fragrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The weeſt wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is mutable. The North wynde purgeth yll vapours, wherfore better it is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two worſt that the wyndowes do open playne North than playne Sowth, althoughe that Ieremy ſayth, from the North depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth all euyl. And alſo it is wrytten in Cantica canto<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan>. Ryſe vp North wynde and come thou Sowth wynde and parfyat my gardayne. Make the hall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a faſſhyon, that the parler be anexed to the heade of the hall. And the buttery and pantry be at the lower ende of the hall, the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler vnder the pantry ſette ſomwhat abaſe, the kychen ſet ſomwhat a baſe from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buttry and pantry, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng with an entry by the wall of the buttry, the paſtry howſe &amp; the larder how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe anexed to the kychen. Than deuyde the lod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynges by the cyrcuyte of the quadryuyall courte, and let the gate howſe be oppoſyt or agaynſt the hall dore (not dyrectly) but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hall dore ſtandynge a baſe, and the gate howſe in the mydle of the front entrynge in to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, let the pryue chambre be anaxed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of aſtate, with other chambres neceſſarye for the buyldynge, ſo that many of the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres maye haue a proſpecte in to the Chapell. If there be an vtter courte made, make it qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dryuyal
<pb facs="tcp:16817:12"/> with howſes of eaſementes, and but one ſtable for horſes of pleaſure, &amp; ſe no fylth nor dong be within the courte, nor caſt at the backe ſyde, but ſe the donge to be caryed farre from the manſyon. Alſo the ſtables and the ſlaughter howſe, a dyery yf any be kept ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be elongated the ſpace of a quarter of a myle from the place. And alſo the backe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and brew howſe ſhuld be a dyſtaunce from the place and from other buyldyng, whan all the manſyon is edyfyed and buylte, yf there be a moote made aboute it, there ſhulde ſome freſſhe ſprynge come to it, and dyuers tymes the moote ought to be ſkowered and kept cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from mudde and wedes. And in no wyſe let not the fylth of the kychen deſcende in to the moote. Furthermore it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous and a pleaſaunt thyng to a manſyon to haue an orcherd of ſoundry fruytes, but it is more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſe to haue a fayre gardain repleted with herbes of aromatyck &amp; redole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſauours. In the gardayne maye be a poole or two for fyſſhe yf the pooles be clene kept. Alſo a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke repleted with dere &amp; conyes is a neceſſarye and a pleaſaunt thyng to be anexed to a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon. A doue howſe alſo is a neceſſary thyng aboute a manſyon place. And amonge other
<pb facs="tcp:16817:12"/> thynges a payre of buttes is a decent thynge aboute a manſyon, &amp; other whyle for a great man neceſſary it is for to paſſe his tyme with bowles in an aly, whan all this is fynyſſhed, and the manſyon replenyſſhed with Imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentꝭ. There muſt be a fyre kept co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually for a ſpace to drye vp the contagyous moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the walles, &amp; the ſauour of the lyme and ſande. And after that a man may ly and dwell in the ſayd manſyon without takynge any inconuenyence of ſyckenes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .v. Chapytre doth ſhewe howe a man ſhulde ordre his howſe conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the Implementes to comforte the ſpyrytes of man. ☜</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath buylt his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyon, and hath his howſes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary aboute his place, yf he haue not howſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſtuffe or implemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the whiche be nedefull, but muſt borowe of his nayghbours, he than is put to a ſhefte
<pb facs="tcp:16817:13"/> and to a great after deale, for theſe men the which do brew in a botyl and bake in a walet, it wyll be long or he can by Iacke a ſalet, yet euery thynge muſt haue a begynnynge, and euery man muſt do after his poſſeſſyons or abylyte, this notwithſtanding better it is not to ſet vp a howſeholde or hoſpytalyte than to ſet vp houſholde lackynge the performacyon of it, as nowe to ron for malt, and by and by for ſalt, nowe to ſend for breade, and by and by to ſende for a ſhepes heade, and nowe to ſende for this, &amp; nowe to ſende for that, and by &amp; by he doth ſend he can not tell for what, ſuch thyngꝭ is no prouyſion, but it is a great abuſyon. Thus a man ſhall leſe his thryfte, and be put to a ſhefte, his goodes ſhall neuer increaſe, and he ſhall not be in reſt nor peace, but euer in carcke and care, for his purſe wyll euer be bare, wherfore I do counceyll euery man, to prouyde for hym ſelfe as ſoone as he can, for yf of implementes he be deſtytuted, men wyll call hym lyght wytted, to ſet vp a great howſe, and is not able to kepe man nor mowſe, wherfore let euery man loke or he lepe, for many cornes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a great hepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:13"/>
               <head>¶ The .vj. Chapytre doth ſhewe howe a man ſhuld ordre his howſe and howſeholde, and to lyue quyetly.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Vho ſoeuer he be that wyll kepe an howſe, he muſt ordre the expenſes of his howſe according to the rent of his landes. And yf he haue no landes he muſt ordre his howſe after his lucre wynnynge or gaynes. For he that wyll ſpende more in his howſe, than the rentes of his landes, or his gaynes doth attayn to, he ſhal fal to pouerte, and neceſſite wyl vrge cauſe and compel hym to ſel his lande, or to waſte his ſtocke, as it is dayly ſene by experye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of many men, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they the whiche wyll exchewe ſuch prody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galyte and inconuenyence, muſt deuyde his rentes porcyon &amp; exſpences, wherby that he doth lyue in to .iii. equal porcyons or partes. ¶ The fyrſt parte muſt ſerue to prouyde for meate and drynke, &amp; all other neceſſary thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for the ſuſtencyon of the howſeholde. ¶ The ſeconde porcyon or parte muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb facs="tcp:16817:14"/> for apparell, not onely for a mannes owne ſelfe, but for all his howſeholde, &amp; for his ſeruauntes wages, deductynge ſomwhat of this porcyon in almes dede to pore neygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours and pore people, fulfyllynge other of the .vii. werkes of mercy. ¶ The .iii. porcyon or parte muſt be reſerued for vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eauſes in tyme of nede, as in ſyckeneſſe, reparacyon of howſes, with many other cotydyall exſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, beſyde rewardes &amp; the charges of a mans laſt end. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do exſyde this ordre he may ſoone fall in det, the whiche is a daungerous thynge many wayes beſyde the bryngynge a man to trouble. And he that is ones behynde hande and in trouble, he can not be in quyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mynde, the whiche doth perturbe the herte, &amp; ſo conſequently doth ſhorten a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes lyfe, wherfore there is no wyſe man but he wyll exchewe this inconuenyence, &amp; wyll caſt before what ſhal folowe after. And in no wyſe to ſette vp a howſeholde, before he hath made prouyſyon to kepe a howſe. For yf a man ſhall bye euery thynge that belongeth to the keping of his howſe with his peny, it wyl be longe or he be ryche, and longe or that he can kepe a good howſe. But he is wyſe in my conceyte that wyll haue or he do ſette vp his
<pb facs="tcp:16817:14"/> howſeholde .ii. or .iii. yeares rent in his cofer. And yf he haue no landes than he muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde for neceſſarye thynges or that he begyn howſeholde, leeſt that he repent hym ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, through the whiche he do fall in to pency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and after that in to ſyckenes &amp; dyſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, lyuyng not quyetly, wherby he ſhal abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyate his lyfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .vij. Chapytre doth ſhewe howe the hed of a howſe, or a howſeholder ſhulde exercyſe hym ſelfe, for the helth of the ſoule &amp; body.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that a man hath prouyded all thynges neceſſary for his howſe and for his howſeholde, expedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent it is for hym to knowe, howe he ſhuld exercyſe hym ſelfe both bodely and ghoſtly. For there is no catholycke or chryſten man lyuyng, but he is bounde in conſcyence to be more circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpecter aboute the welth of his ſoule then the helth of his body. Our ſauyour Ieſus Chryſt ſayth, what ſhall it profyte vnto man yf he geat all the worlde and leſe hym ſelfe, and bryng hym
<pb facs="tcp:16817:15"/> ſelfe to a detryme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherfore it appereth that a man ought to be circumſpecte for the helth and welth of his ſoule. For he is bounde ſo to lyue, that nyght and day and at all houres he ſhulde be redy, than whan he is called for to departe out of this worlde he ſhuld nat feare to dye, ſaying theſe wordes with ſaynt Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe. I feare not to dye, bycauſe we haue a good god, whan a man hath prepared for his ſoule, and hath ſubdued ſenſualyte, and that he hath brought hym ſelfe in a trade, or a vſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of a ghoſtly or a catholycke lyuynge in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruyng the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of God, than he muſt ſtudy to rule and to gouern them the whiche be in his howſeholde, or vnder his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody or domynyon, to ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be not ydle, for kynge Henry the eyght ſayd when he was yong, ydlenes is chefe maiſtres of vyces all. And alſo the heade of a howſe muſt ouer ſe that they the which be vnder his tuyſſyon ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue god the holy dayes as dylygently, yee and more dylygentler than to do theyr worke the feryall dayes, refraynynge them from vyce and ſynne, compellynge them to obſerue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of God, ſpecyally to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe ſwearers, for in all the worlde there is not ſuche odyble ſwearyng as is vſed in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:15"/> ſpecyally amonge youth &amp; chyldren, which is a deteſtable thyng to here it, and no man doth go aboute to punyſſhe it. Suche thynges reformed than may an howſeholder be glad not ceſſynge to inſtruct them the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be ygnorant, but alſo he muſt contynewe in ſhewynge good example of lyuynge, than may he reioyſe in God and be mery, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che myrth &amp; reioyſyng doth lengthen a mans lyfe, and doth expell ſyckenes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .viij. Chapytre doth ſhew howe a man ſhulde ordre hym ſelfe in ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge and watchynge, and in weryng his apparell.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han a man hath exercyſed hym ſelfe in the daye tyme as is reherſed, he may ſlepe ſoundly and ſurely in god what chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſoeuer do fortune in the nyght. Moderate ſlepe is moſte prayſed for it doth make parfyte degeſtyon, it doth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe the blode, and doth qualyfye the heate of the lyuer, it doth acuate, quycken, &amp; refreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the memory, it doth reſtore nature, and
<pb facs="tcp:16817:16"/> doth quyet all the humours &amp; pulſes in man, and doth anymate, and doth comforte all the naturall and anymall and ſpyrytuall powers of man. And ſuch moderate ſlepe is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſyght of God the premyſſes in the aforeſayd Chapytre obſerued and kept. And contraryly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moderate ſlepe and ſluggyſhnes doth humecte and maketh lyght the brayne, it doth ingendre rewme and impoſtumes, it is euyll for the palſy whyther it be vnyuerſall or partyculer, it is euyll for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fallynge ſyckenes called Epilencia, Analencia, &amp; Cathalencia, Appopleſia, Soda, with all other infyrmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes in the heade, for it induceth and cauſeth oblyuyouſnes, for it doth obfuſke and doth obnebulate the memorye and the quyckenes of wyt. And ſhortly to conclude it doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbe the naturall, and anymall, and ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall powers of man. And ſpecyally it doth inſtygate and lede a man to ſynne, and doth induce and infer breuyte of lyfe, &amp; deteſtably it diſpleaſeth God. Our lorde Ieſu Chryſte dyd not onely byd or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de his dyſcyples to watche, but dyd anymat them and al other ſo to do ſaying. I ſay not onely to you wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, but to all men I ſay watche. And to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſaid, myghteſt not thou one houre wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:16817:16"/> with me, althoughe theſe holy ſcryptures with many other mo the which I myght ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate for me, althoughe they be not greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to this ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet it may ſtande here with my purpoſe &amp; matter without reprehenſyon. Theſe matters here nede not to be reherſed, wherfore I do returne to my purpoſe, and do ſay that the moderacyon of ſlepe ſhulde be meſured accordyng to the natural co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexyon of man, and in any wyſe to haue a reſpect to the ſtrength and the debylyte to age &amp; youth, and to ſyckenes &amp; helth of man. ¶ Fyrſte as concernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall complexyon of man, as ſanguyne and colorycke men .vii. houres is ſuffycyent for them. And nowe conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the imbecyllyte and wekenes of nature a flemytycke man may ſlepe .ix. houres or mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. Melancoly men may take theyr pleaſure, for they be receptacle and the dragges of all the other humoures. ¶ Secondaryly youth and age wolde haue temporau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in ſlepynge. ¶ Thyrdly ſtrength maye ſuffre a brount in watche, the whiche debylyte and wekenes can not. As I wyl ſhew by a famylyer example. There were two men ſet at the dyce togither a day and a nyght &amp; more, the weke man ſaid to hym I can playe no longer. The ſtronge
<pb facs="tcp:16817:17"/> man ſayde to hym fye on the benche whyſtler wylt thou ſterte away nowe. The weke man to ſatyſfye the ſtronge mannes mynde, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ꝓyted, &amp; deſyre playeth with his felow throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he doth kyl hym ſelfe. The ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge man doth hym ſelfe lytel pleaſure all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges conſydered, the whiche I do paſſe ouer, wherfore I wyll retourne to the ſycke man, whiche maye ſlepe at all tymes whan that he maye get it, but yf he maye ſlepe at any tyme beſt it is for hym to refrayn from ſlepe in the day, &amp; to take his naturall reſt at nyght whan all thynges is or ſhulde be at reſt and peace, but he muſt do as his infyrmyte wyll permyt and ſuffre. whole men of what age or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexyon ſoeuer they be of ſhuld take theyr na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reſt and ſlepe in the nyght, &amp; to exchew merydyall ſlepe. But an nede ſhall compell a man to ſlepe after his meate, let hym make a pauſe, and than let hym ſtand and leane and ſlepe agaynſt a cupborde, or els let hym ſytte vp ryght in a chayre &amp; ſlepe. Slepynge after a full ſtomacke doth ingendre dyuerſe infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myties, it doth hurte the ſplen, it relaxeth the ſynewes, it doth ingendre the dropſyes and the gowte, and doth make a man loke euyl co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loured. Beware of Veneryous actes before
<pb facs="tcp:16817:17"/> the fyrſte ſlepe, and ſpecyally beware of ſuch thynges after dyner or after a full ſtomacke, for it doth ingendre the crampe, the gowte, and other diſpleaſures. To bedwarde be you mery, or haue mery company aboute you, ſo that to bedwarde no anger nor heuynes, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe nor pencyfulnes do trouble or diſquyet you. To bedwarde and alſo in the mornyng vſe to haue a fyre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your chambre to waſt and conſume the euyll vapours within the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, for the breath of man maye putryfye the ayre within the chambre. I do aduertyſe you not to ſtande nor to ſyt by the fyre, but ſtand or ſyt a good waye of from the fyre takynge the flauour of it, for fyre doth aryfye &amp; doth drye vp a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes blode, and doth make ſterke the ſynewes &amp; ioyntes of man. In the nyght let the wyndowes of your howſe, ſpecially of your chambre be cloſed, whan you be in your bed lye a lytel whyle on your left ſyde, &amp; ſlepe on your ryght ſyde. And whan you do wake of your fyrſte ſlepe make water yf you fele your bladder charged, and than ſlepe on the lefte ſyde, and loke as ofte as you do wake ſo oft tourne yourſelfe in the bed from the one ſyde to the other. To ſlepe grouelynge vpon the ſtomacke and belly is not good, oneles
<pb facs="tcp:16817:18"/> the ſtomacke be ſlow and tarde of digeſtyon, but better it is to lay your hande or your bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felowes hande ouer your ſtomacke, than to lye grouelyng. To ſlepe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backe vpryght is vtterly to be abhorred, when y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you do ſlepe let not your necke nother your ſhoulders, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your handes nor fete, nor no other place of your body lye bare vndyſcouered. Slepe not with an empty ſtomacke, nor ſlepe not af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that you haue eaten meate one houre or two after. In your beed lye with your heed ſomwhat hygh, leſt that the meate which is in your ſtomacke thorow eructuacyons or ſome other cauſe aſcend to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gryfe of the ſtomacke Let your nyght cap be of ſkarlet, &amp; this I do aduertyſe you for to cauſe to be made a good thycke quylt of cotton, or els of pure flockes or of clene woull, and let the couerynge of it be of whyte fuſtyan, and laye it on the fether beed that you do lye on, and in your beed lye not to hote nor colde, but in a temporaunce. Olde auncyent doctours of Phyſycke ſayth. viii. houres of ſlepe in So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer &amp; .ix. houres of ſlepe in wynter is ſuffycyent for any man, but I do thynke that ſlepe ought to be taken as the complexyon of man is, whan you do ryſe in the morenynge, ryſe with myrth and
<pb facs="tcp:16817:18"/> remembre God. Let your hoſen be bruſſhed within and without, and flauour the inſyde of them agaynſt the fyre, vſe lynen ſockes or lynnen hoſen next your legges, whan you be out of your bedde ſtretche forth your legges and armes and your body, coughe and ſpyt and than go to your ſtole to make your ege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyon, and exonerate your ſelfe at all tymes that nature wold expell. For yf you do make any reſtryction in kepynge your egeſtion or your vryne or ventoſyte, it maye put you to dyſpleaſure in bredyng dyuers infyrmyties. After you haue euacuated your body, &amp; truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your poyntes, kayme your heade oft, and ſo do dyuerſe tymes in the daye. And waſſhe your handes and wreſtes, your face and eyes and your tethe with colde water, &amp; after that you be apparelled walke in your gardayne or parke a thouſande pace or two, &amp; than great and noble men doth vſe to here maſſe, &amp; other men that can not do ſo but muſt applye theyr buſynes, doth ſerue God with ſome prayers ſurrendrynge thankes to hym for his many folde goodnes, with aſkyng mercye for theyr offences, &amp; before you go to your refection moderatly exercyſe your body with ſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or playing at the tennys, or caſtynge a
<pb facs="tcp:16817:19"/> bowle, or payſyng wayghtes or plomettes of ledde in your handes or ſome other thynge to open your poores, and to augment naturall hete. At dyner &amp; ſupper vſe not to drynke of ſondry drynkes, &amp; eate not of dyuers meates but fede of two or thre dyſſhes at the moſte. After that you haue dyned &amp; ſupped laboure not by and by after, but make a pauſe ſyttyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge or ſtandyng vpright the ſpace of an houre or more with ſome paſtyme, drynke not moch after dyner. At your ſupper vſe light meates of digeſtyon, &amp; refrayne from groſe meates, go not vnto bedde with a ful nor emptye ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke. And after your ſupper make a pauſe or you go to bedde, and go to bed as I ſayde with myrth. Furthermore as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng your apparrell in wynter nexte your ſherte vſe to were a petycote of ſkarlet, your doubletvſe at pleſure, but I do aduertyſe you to lyne your Iacket vnder this faſſhyon or maner, by you fyne ſkyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of whyte lambe &amp; blacke lambe, and let your ſkynner cut both the ſortꝭ of the ſkynnes in ſmale peces tryangle wyſe, lyke halfe a quarel of a glaſe wyndow. And than ſewe togyther a whyte pece and a blacke lyke a hole quarell of a glaſſe wyndowe, &amp; ſo ſewe vp togyther quarell wyſe as moche as wyll
<pb facs="tcp:16817:19"/> lyne your Iacket, this fur for holſomnes is prayſed aboue ſables or any other furre, your exteryall apparell vſe accordynge to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. In ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer vſe to were a ſkarlet petycote made of ſtamele or lynſye wolſye. In wynter and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer kepe nor your hed to hote nor byn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de it to ſtrayte, kepe euer your necke warme. In ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer kepe your necke and face from the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, vſe to were gloues made of goote ſkyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes perfumed with amber degrece. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware in ſtandynge or lying on the grownde in the reflyxyon of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, but be mouable. If you ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon or talke with any man, ſtande not ſtyll in one place yf it be on the bare grownde, or graſſe, or ſtones, but be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable in ſuch places, ſtande nor ſyt vpon no ſtone nor ſtones, ſtand nor ſyt long bareheed vnder a vawte of ſtone. Alſo beware that you do not lye in olde chambres whiche be not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed, ſpecyally ſuch chambres as myſe, rat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and ſnayles reſorteth vnto, lye not in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che chambres the whiche be depryued clene from the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; open ayre, nor lye in no lowe chamber except it be borded. Beware that you take no colde on your feete and legges, and of al wether beware that you do not ryde nor go in great and impyteous wyndes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:20"/>
               <head>¶ The .ix. Chapytre doth ſhewe that replecyon or ſurfetynge doth moche harme to nature / and that abſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence is the chefyſt medyſon of all medyſons.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Alen declarying Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates ſentence vpon eatyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to moche meate ſaith. More meate than accordeth with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is named replecyon, or a ſurfete. Reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon or a ſurfet is taken as well by gurgyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons or to moche drynkynge, as it is taken by epulacyon of eatynge of crude meate, or eatynge more meate than doth ſuffyce or can be truely dygeſted. Or els replecyon or a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt is whan the ſtomacke is farced or ſtuft, or repleted with to moche drynke &amp; meate, that the lyuer whiche is the fyre vnder the potte is ſubpreſſed that he can not naturally nor true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decoct, defye, ne dygeſt the ſuperabundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of meate &amp; drynke the which is in the potte or ſtomacke, wherfore dyuers tymes theſe im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pedymentes doth folowe, the tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is depry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his offyce to ſpeke, the wyttes or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſys be dull &amp; obnebulated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon. Slouth
<pb facs="tcp:16817:20"/> and ſluggyſhnes conſequently foloweth, the appetyde is withdrawen. The heade is lyght and doth ake, and full of fantaſyes, &amp; dyuers tymes ſome be ſo ſopytyd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the malt worme playeth the deuyll ſo faſt in the heade, that all the worlde ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth rownde aboute on wheles, then both the pryncepall membres &amp; the offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall membres doth fayle of theyr ſtrength, yet the pulſys be full of agylyte. Such reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon ſpecyally ſuche gurgytacyons doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender dyuers infyrmytes thorowe the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che breuite and ſhortnes of lyfe doth folowe. For the wyſe man ſayth, that ſurfetes do kyll many men, and temporaunce doth prolonge the lyfe. And alſo it is wrytten Eccle. xx.xvii. That there doth dye many mo by ſurfette, than there doth by the ſworde, for as I ſayde ſurfetyng ingendreth many infyrmytes, as the Idropyſes, the gowtꝭ, lepored, ſauſfleme &amp; pymples in the face, veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t impreſſyons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndygeſt humours, opylacyons, feuers, and putryfaccyons. And alſo it doth perturbate the heade, the eyes, the tounge, and the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, with many other infyrmyties. For as Galen ſayth, ouer moche replecyon or ſurfe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, cauſeth ſtrangulacion and ſoden death, for as I ſayde the ſtomacke is ſo inferced,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:22"/> and the lyuer is ſo ſore obpreſſed that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate and the poores be extyncted, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abſtynence for this matter is the moſte beſt and the parfyteſt medyſone that can be. And in no wyſe eate no meate vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme the ſtomacke be euacuated of all yll humours by vomet or other conuenyent wayes, for els crude and rawe humours vndygeſted wyll multiply in the body to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> detryment of man. Two meales a daye is ſuffycyent for a reſt man, and a labourer maye eate thre tymes a day, &amp; he that doth eate ofter lyueth a beeſtly lyfe. And he that doth eate more than ones in a day, I aduertyſe hym that the fyrſte refec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon or meale be dygeſted or that he do eate the ſeconde refeccyon or meale. For there is nothynge more hurtfull for mans body than to eate meate vpon meate vndygeſted. For the laſt refeccyon or meale wyll let the dyge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyon of the fyrſte refeccyon or meale. Alſo ſondry meates of dyuers operacyons eaten at one refeccion or meale is not laudable, nor it is not good to ſyt longe at dyner and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. An houre is ſuffycyent to ſyt at dyner, and not ſo longe at ſupper. Englande hath an euyll vſe in ſyttynge longe at dyner and at ſupper. And Englyſſhe men hath an euyll
<pb facs="tcp:16817:22"/> vſe, for at the begynnynge at dyner and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per he wyll fede on groſe meates. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt meates which be holſome and nutratyue and lyeth of digeſtion is kept for ſeruauntes, for whan the good meate doth come to the table thorowe fedyng vpon groſe meate, the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyde is extynct whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good meet doth come to the table, but ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mynde is ſo auydous althoughe he haue eate ynoughe whan he ſeth better meate come before hym agaynſt his ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petyde he wyll eate, wherupon doth come re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plecyon and ſurfetes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .x. Chapytre treateth of all ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of drynkes, as of water, of wyne, of ale, of bere, of cyder, of meade, of metheglyn, and of whay.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ater is one of the foure Elementꝭ, of the whiche dyuerſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours or drynkes for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſuſtynaunce be made of, takyng theyr orygynall and ſubſtaunce of it, as ale, bere, meade, and metheglyn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> water is not holſome ſole by it ſelfe for an englyſſhe man, conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge
<pb facs="tcp:16817:23"/> the contrarye vſage, whiche is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curraunt with nature, water is colde, ſlowe, and ſlacke of dygeſtyon. The beſt water is rayne water ſo be it that it be clene and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken. Next to it is ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng water, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the doth ſwyftly ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne from the Eeſt in to the weſt vpon ſtones or pybles. The thyrde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be prayſed is ryuer or broke water, the which is clere ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng on pibles and grauayl. Standynge waters the whiche be refreſſhed with a freſſhe ſpryng is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, but ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng waters, and well waters, to the whiche the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hath no reflyxyon, althoughe they be lyghter then other ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng waters be, yet they be not ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable. And let euery man be ware of all waters the whiche be ſtandynge, and be putryfyed with froth, duckemet, and mudde, for yf they bake, or brewe, or dreſſe meate with it, it ſhall ingender many infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytes. The water y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which euery man ought to dreſſe his meate with all, or ſhall vſe bakyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, or bruyng, let it be ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng, and put it in veſſels y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may ſtande there .ii. or .iii. houres or it be occupyed, than ſtrayne the vpper par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te thoroughe a thycke lynnyn cloth, and caſt the inferyall parte away. If any man do vſe to drynke water with wyne, let it be purely
<pb facs="tcp:16817:23"/> ſtrayned, and than ſeth it and after it be cold let hym put it to his wyne, but better it is to drynke with wyne ſtylled waters, ſpecyally the water of ſtrawberes or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of buglos or the water of endyne, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of cycory, or the waters of ſouthyſtell, and dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delyon. And yf any man be combred with the ſtone or doth burne in the pudibunde places, vſe to drynke with whyte wyne the water of hawes, and the water of mylke, loke for this matter in a boke of my makyng named the breuyary of health.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of wyne.</head>
                  <p>¶ All maner of wynes be made of grapes, excepte reſpyſe the whiche is made of a bery. Choſe your wyne after this ſorte, it muſt be fyne, fayre, &amp; clere to the eye, it muſt be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graunt and redolent hauynge a good odour and flauour in the noſe, it muſt ſpryncle in the cup whan it is drawne or put out of the pot in to the cup, it muſt be colde &amp; pleaſaunt in the mouth, and it muſt be ſtrong and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll of ſubſtaunce: And than moderatly dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken it doth acuate and doth quycken a mans wyttes, it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the hert, it doth ſcowre the lyuer, ſpecyally yf it be whyte wyn it doth reioyce all the powers of man, and doth now
<pb facs="tcp:16817:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> ryſſhe them, it doth ingender good blode, it doth comforte and doth nouryſſhe the brayne and all the body, and it reſolueth fleume, it ingendreth heate, and it is good agaynſt he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynes and pencyfulnes, it is ful of agylyte, wherfore it is medſonable, ſpecyally whyte wyne, for it doth mundyfye and clenſe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; ſores. Furthermore the better the wyne is, the better humours it doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, wyne muſt not be to newe nor to olde, but hyghe wynes as malmyſe maye be kepe longe. And bycauſe wyne is full of fumoſyte, it is good therfore to alaye it with water. wynes hyghe and hote of operacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth comfort olde men and women, but there is no wyne good for chyldren &amp; maydens, for in hyghe Almayne there is no mayde ſhall drynke no wyne, but ſtyl ſhe ſhal drynke water vnto ſhe be maried, the vſuall drynke there &amp; in other hyghe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres for youth is fountayn water, for in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry towne is a fountayne or a ſhalowe wel, to the which all people that be yonge &amp; ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ hath a confluence and a recourſe to drynke. Meane wynes as wynes of Gaſcony, fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wynes, &amp; ſpecyally raynyſſhe wyne that is fyned is good with meate, ſpecyally claret wyne. It is not good to drynke nother wyne
<pb facs="tcp:16817:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> nor ale before a man doth eate ſomwhat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe there be olde fantaſtycall ſayingꝭ to the contrarye. Alſo theſe hote wynes as mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſye, wyne courſe, wyne greke, romanyſk, romny, ſecke, alygaunt, baſterde, tyre, oſay, Muſcadell, caprycke, tynt, roberdany, with other hote wynes be not good to drynke with meate, but after meate, &amp; with oyſters, with ſaledes, with fruyte a draught or two may be ſuffered. Olde men maye drynke as I ſayde hyghe wynes at theyr pleaſure. Furthermore all ſwete wynes and groſe wynes doth make a man fatte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of ale.</head>
                  <p>¶ Ale is made of malte and water, and they the which do put any other thynge to ale then is reherſed, except yeſt, barme, or godeſgood, doth ſofyſtical theyr ale. Ale for an englyſſhe man is a naturall drynke. Ale muſt haue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe propertyes, it muſt be freſſhe and cleare, it muſt not be ropy nor ſmoky, nor it muſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no weft nor tayle. Ale ſhuld not be dronke vnder .v. dayes olde. Newe ale is vnholſome for all men. And ſowre ale and deade ale the which doth ſtande a tylt is good for no man. Barly malte maketh better ale the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oten mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or any other corne doth, it doth ingendre
<pb facs="tcp:16817:25"/> groſe humoures, but yette it maketh a man ſtronge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of bere.</head>
                  <p>¶ Bere is made of malte, of hoppes, and wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, it is a naturall drynke for a dutche man. And nowe of late dayes it is moche vſed in Englande to the detryment of many englyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe men, ſpecyally it kylleth them the which be troubled with the colycke and the ſtone &amp; the ſtrangulion, for the drynke is a colde drynke: yet it doth make a man fat, and doth inflate the bely, as it doth appere by the dutche mens faces &amp; belyes. If the bere be well ſerued and be fyned &amp; not newi,t doth qualyfy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heat of the lyuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of cyder.</head>
                  <p>¶ Cyder is made of the iuce of peeres, or of the iuce of aples, &amp; other whyle cyder is made of both, but the beſt cyder is made of cleane peeres the which be dulcet, but the beeſt is not prayſed in phyſycke, for cyder is colde of ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racyon, and is full of ventoſyte, wherfore it doth ingendre euyll humours, and doth ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to moche the naturall heate of man, &amp; doth let dygeſtyon, and doth hurte the ſtomacke, but they the which be vſed to it, yf it be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in haruyſt it doth lytell harme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of meade.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:25"/>
                  <p>¶ Meade is made of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and water boyled both togyther, yf it be fyned and pure it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth helth, but it is not good for them the whiche haue the Ilyacke or the colycke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of metheglyn.</head>
                  <p>¶ Metheglyn is made of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny &amp; water, and herbes boyled and ſodden togyther, yf it be fyned and ſtale, it is better in the regyment of helth than meade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of whay.</head>
                  <p>¶ whay yf it be well ordered, ſpecyally thai whay the which doth come of butter, is a tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porate drynke and is moyſt, and it doth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe, it doth clenſe the breſt, and doth purge redde colour, and good for ſauſfleme faces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of poſet ale.</head>
                  <p>¶ Poſet ale is made with hote mylke &amp; colde ale, it is a temporate drynke, and is good for a hote lyuer, and for hote feuers, ſpecyally yf colde herbes be ſoden in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of coyte.</head>
                  <p>¶ Coyte is a drynke made of water, in the which is layde a ſowre and a ſalt leuyn .iii. or .iiii. houres, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is dronke, it is a vſual dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in Pycardy, in Flaundres, in Holande, in Brabant, and Selande.</p>
                  <p>¶ To ſpeake of a ptyſan, or of oxymel, or of
<pb facs="tcp:16817:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> aqua vite, or of Ipocras, I do paſſe ouer at this tyme, for I do make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyon of it in the Breuyary of health.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xi. Chapytre treateth of breade. ☜</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vycen ſayth, that breed made of whete maketh a man fatte, ſpecyally when the breade is made of newe whete, and it doth ſet a man in temporau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Breade made of fyne flower without leuyn is ſlowe of dygeſtyon, but it doth nouryſſhe moche yf it be truely ordered and well baken, whan the breade is leuened it is ſoone dygeſted as ſome olde Aucthours ſayth, but theſe dayes is proued the contrary by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke of men, for leuyn is heuy and ponderous. Breade hauynge to moche bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in it is not laudable. In Rome and other hyghe countres theyr loues of breade be lytell bygger then a walnot, and many lytell loues be ioyned togyther, the whiche doth ſerue for great men, and it is ſafferonde, I prayſe it not. I do loue manchet breade, and great lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues the whiche he well mowlded and thorowe
<pb facs="tcp:16817:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> baken, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brande abſtracted and abiected, and that is good for all ages. Meſtlyng breade is made halfe of whete and halfe of Rye. And there is alſo meſtlyng made halfe of rye and halfe of barly. And yll people wyll put whete and barly togyther, breade made of theſe afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſayde grayne or cornes, thus poched togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maye fyll the gutte, but it ſhall neuer do good to man, no more than horſe breade or breade made of beanes and peaſon ſhall do, howbeit this matter doth go moche by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon or the bryngyng vp of the people, the which haue ben nouriſſhed or nutryfyde with ſuche breade. I do ſpeake nowe in barlyes or maltes parte to be eaten and alſo dronken, I ſuppoſe it is to moche for one grayne, fox barly doth ingender colde humours, and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and beanes, and the ſubſtaunce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge from theym repletyth a man with ventoſyte, but and yf a man haue a luſt or a ſenſuall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petyd to eate and drynke of a grayne byſyde malte or barlye, let hym eate and drynke of it the whiche maye be made of otes. For hauer cakes in ſcotlande is many a good lorde and lordes dyſſhe. And yf it wyll make good ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cakes conſequently it wyll do make good drynke or euyl, euery thyng as it is handled.
<pb facs="tcp:16817:27"/> For it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prouerbe, God may ſende a man good meate, but the deuyll may ſende an euyll coke to dyſtrue it, wherfore gentyll bakers ſophyſtycate not your breade made of pure whete, yf you do where euyl ale brewers and ale wyues for theyr euyl brewyng &amp; euyl meaſure, ſhuld clacke and ryng theyr tankar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des at dym myls dale, I wold you ſhuld ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke out the remnaunt of your ſackes ſtandyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes vp to the harde chynne and .iii. ynches aboue, that whan you do come out of the water you myght ſhake your eares as a ſpanyell that veryly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of the water. Gentyll bakers make good breade, for good breade doth comforte, confyrme, and doth ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyſſhe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes herte, beſyde the propertyes reherſed. Hote breade is vnholſome for any man, for it doth lye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke lyke a ſpon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge hauſtyng vndecoct humours, yet the ſmel of newe breade is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable to the heade and to the herte. ¶ Soden breade as ſymnels and crackenels, and breade baken vpon a ſtone, or vpon yron, and breade that ſaffron is in, is not laudable. Burnt breade and harde cruſtꝭ, &amp; paſty cruſtes, doth ingendre color, aduſte, and melancoly humours, wherfore chyp the vpper cruſt of your breade. And who ſo doth
<pb facs="tcp:16817:27"/> vſe to eate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeconde cruſt after meate, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man leane. And ſo doth wheten breade the which is ful of brande. ¶ Breade the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is nutrytyue &amp; prayſed in phyſycke ſhuld haue theſe propertes. Fyrſte it muſt be newe, but a daye &amp; a nyght olde, nor it is not good whan it is paſt .iiii. or .v. dayes olde, except the loues be great, nor it muſt not be moldy nor muſty, it muſt be well muldyd, it muſt be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe bake, it muſte be lyght &amp; not heuye, and it muſt be temporatly ſalted. Olde breade or ſtale breade doth dry vp the blode, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall moyſter of man, &amp; it doth ingender euyll humours, and is euyll and tarde of dygeſtyon, wherfore there is no ſurfet ſo euyll as the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet of eatynge of euyll breade.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xij. Chapyter treateth of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, of ſewe, of ſtewpottes, of grewell, of fyrme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, of peaſe potage, of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mylke, of ryce potage, of cawdels, of culleſes, and of other brothes.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:28"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L maner of ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyd thynges as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſewe, &amp; all other brothes doth replete a man that eateth theym with ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>toſyte. Potage is not ſo moch vſed in all cryſtendom as it is vſed in Englande. Potage is made of the ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quor in the which fleſſhe is ſoden in, with put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng to chopped herbes, and otemel and ſalt. The herbes with the whiche potage is made with all, yf they be purc, good, and clene, not warme eaten, nor infected with the corrupt ayre deſcendynge vpon them, doth comforte many men, the ventofyte notwithſtandyng. But for aſmoch as dyuers tymes, many par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Englande is infected with the peſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, thorow the corrupcyon of the ayre, the which doth infecte the herbes. In ſuch tymes it is not good to make any potage, nor to eate no potage. In certayn placs beyonde ſee where as I haue traueyled in, in the peſtylen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce tyme a generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement hath ben ſent from the ſuperyoryte to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monalte, that no man ſhuld eate herbes in ſuche infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous tymes.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:28"/>
                  <head>¶ Of ſewe and ſtewpottes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Sewe and ſtewpottes, and grewell made with otmell, in all the which no herbes be put in, can do lytel diſpleaſure, except that it doth replete a man with ventoſyte, but it relaxeth the belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of fyrmente.</head>
                  <p>¶ Fyrmente is made of whete and mylke, in the whiche yf fleſſhe be ſoden, to eate it is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, for it is harde of dygeſtyon, but whan it is dygeſted it doth nouryſſhe, and it doth ſtrength a man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of peaſe potage &amp; beane potage.</head>
                  <p>¶ Peaſe potage and beane potage doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete a man with ventoſyte. Peaſe potage is better than beane potage, for it is ſooner dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, &amp; leſſer of ventoſyte, they both be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtercyne and do clenſe the body. They be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytent of nutryment, but beane potage doth increaſe groſſe humours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of almon mylke &amp; of ryce potage.</head>
                  <p>¶ Almon mylke and ryce potage, Almone be hote and moyſte, it doth comforte the breſt and it doth mollyfye the bely, and prouoketh vryne. Ryce potage made with almon mylke doth reſtore and doth comforte nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of ale brues, caudelles &amp; coleſſes.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:29"/>
                  <p>¶ Ale brues, caudelles, and coleſſes for weke men and feble ſtomackes, the whiche can not eate ſolydate meate is ſuſtered. But caudels made with hempe ſede, and colleſſes made of ſhrympes doth comforte blode and nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ſoppes and other brothes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ſoppes &amp; other brothes of what kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or ſubſtaunce ſoeuer they be made of, they doth ingender ventoſyte, wherfore they be not good nor holſome for the colycke nor the Illycke, nor other inflatyue impedymentes or ſyckeneſſes, ſpecyally yf ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny be in it, the ſayinges of Plyne, Galene, Auycene, with other Aucthours notwithſtandynge, for in theſe dayes experyence teacheth vs contrary to theyr ſayinges &amp; wrytyngꝭ, for althoughe the nature of man be not altered, yet it is we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and nothynge ſo ſtronge nowe as when they lyued. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xiij. Chapitre treateth of whyt meate, as of egges, butter, cheſe, mylke, crayme. &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N England there is no egges vſed to be eaten, but hen egges: wherfore I wyl fyrſt wryte &amp; pertract of hen egges. The yolkes of
<pb facs="tcp:16817:29"/> hen egges be cordyalles, for it is temporatly hote. The whyte of an egge is viſcus &amp; colde and ſlacke of digeſtyon, and doth not ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der good blode, wherfore whoſoeuer that wyl eate an egge, let the egge be newe, and roſte hym reare and eate hym, or els poche hym for poched egges be beſt at nyght, &amp; newe reare roſted egges be good in the mornynge ſo be it they be tyred with a lytell ſalte and ſuger, than they be nutryue. In Turkey and other hyghe chryſtyan landes anexed to it, they vſe to ſeth two or thre buſſhels of egges togither harde, and pull of the ſhels, &amp; ſowſe them, and kepe them to eate at al tymes, but hard egges be ſlowe and ſlacke of dygeſtyon, and doth nutryfye the body groſly. Roſted egges be better than ſodden, fryed egges be nought, Ducke egges &amp; geſe egges I do not prayſe, but feſaunt egges and partreges egges phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycke ſyngulerly doth prayſe.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of butter.</head>
                  <p>¶ Butter made of crayme, and is moyſte of operacion, it is good to eate in the mornyng before other meates, Frenche men wyll eate it after meate. But eaten with other meatꝭ it doth not onely nowryſſhe, but it is good for the breſte and lunges, and alſo it relaxe and
<pb facs="tcp:16817:30"/> mollyfye the bely, douche men doth eate it at all tymes in the daye, the whiche I dyd not prayſe when I dyd dwell amonge them / con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderyng that butter is vnctyous, and euery thynge that is vnctyous is noyſome to the ſtomacke for as moche as it maketh lubryfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon. And alſo euery thyng that is vnctious That is to ſay butteryſhe, oyle, greſe, or fat dothe ſwymme aboue in the brynkes of the ſtomacke, as the fatnes dothe ſwymme abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in a boylynge potte, the exceſſe of ſuche nawtacyon or ſuperfyce wyll aſcende to the oryſe of the ſtomacke, and doth make eructua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyons / wherfore eatynge of moche butter at one refection is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable, nor it is nor good for theym the whiche be in any ague or feuer, for the ventuoſyte of it doth auge and augment the heate of the lyuer, a lytell porcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is good for euery man in the morenynge yf it be newe made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Cheſe.</head>
                  <p>¶ Cheſe is made of mylke, yet there is .iiii. ſortes of cheſe: whiche is to ſaye, grene cheſe, ſofte cheſe, harde cheſe, and ſpermyſe / Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cheſe is not called grene by the reaſon of colour, but for the newnes of it / for the whey is not halfe preſſed out of it, and in operacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:16817:30"/> it is colde and moyſte. Softe cheſe not to new nor to olde is beſt, for in operacyon it is hote and moyſte. Harde cheſe is hote and dry and euyll to dygeſt. Spermyſe is a cheſe the which is made with curdes and with the iuce of herbes, to tell the nature of it I can not / conſyderynge that euery mylke wyfe maye put many iuces of herbes of ſondry operacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on &amp; vertue, one not agreynge with another. But and yf they dyd knowe what they dyd gomble togyther without trewe compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, and I knowynge the herbes, then I coulde tell the operacyon of ſpermyſe cheſe, yet beſyde theſe .iiii. natures of cheſe, there is a cheſe called a rewene cheſe, the whiche yf it be well orderyd doth paſſe all other cheſes no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne exceſſe taken. But take the beſt cheſe of all theſe reherſyd, yf a latel do good and pleaſur The ouerplus doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre groſe humours for it is harde of dygeſtyon, it maketh a man coſtyfe and it is not good for the ſtone. Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that is good oughte not be to harde nor to ſofte, but betwyxt both, it ſhuld not be towgh nor bruttell, it ought not to be ſwete nor ſow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, nor tarte, nor to ſalt, nor to freſſhe, it muſt be of good ſauour &amp; taledge, nor full of iyes nor mytes, nor magottes / yet in hyghalmen
<pb facs="tcp:16817:31"/> the cheſe the whiche is full of magotes is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led there the beſt cheſe, and they wyll eate the great magotꝭ as faſt as we do eate comfetꝭ.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Mylke,</head>
                  <p>Mylke of a woman, and the mylke of a gote is a good reſtoratyue, wherfore theſe mylkes be good for them that be in a conſumpcyon, and for the great temperaunce the whiche is in them it doth nowryſſhe moche.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cowes mylke and ewes mylke, ſo it be the beeſtes be yonge and do go in good paſture, the mylke is nutrytyue and doth humect and moyſteth the membres, and doth mundyfye and clenſe the entrayles, and doth alleuyat &amp; mytygate the payne of the lunges &amp; the breſt but it is not good for them the whiche haue gurgulacyons in the bely, nor it is not al the beſt for ſanguyne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but it is very good for melancoly men, &amp; for olde men and chyldren ſpecyally yf it be foddyn, addynge to it a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ſugre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Crayme,</head>
                  <p>¶ Crayme the whiche dothe not ſtande lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge on the mylke &amp; ſoddyn with a lytell ſuger is nowryſſhynge. Clowtyd crayme and rawe crayme put togyther, is eaten more for a ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuall apetyde, than for any good nowryſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="tcp:16817:31"/> Rawe crayme vndecocted eaten with ſtrawberyes, or hurtes is a rurall mans ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket. I haue knowen ſuche bankettes hath put men in ieoperdy of theyr lyues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Almon butter.</head>
                  <p>¶ Almon butter made with fyne ſuger and good roſe water, and eaten with the flowers of many vyolettes, is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable dyſſhe, ſpecyally in lent whan the vyoletꝭ be fragra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it reioyſeth the herte: it doth comforte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: &amp; doth qualyfye the heate of the lyuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Beene butter.</head>
                  <p>¶ Beene butter, is vſed moche in lent in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers countres, it is good for plowmen to fyl the panche, it doth ingender groſe humours, it doth replete a man with ventoſyte.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xiiij. Chapytre, treatyth of Fyſſhe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all nacyons &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tres, Englande is beſte ſeruyd of Fyſſhe, not onely of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſee fyſſhe, but alſo of freſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe water fyſſhe, and of all maner of ſortes of ſalte fyſſhe.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of See fyſſhe.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:32"/>
                  <p>¶ Fyſſhes of the ſee the which haue ſkales or many fynnes, be more holſomer than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> freſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe water fyſſhe, the whiche be in ſtandynge waters. The elder a fyſſhe is ſo moche he is the better, ſo be it that the fyſſhe be ſofte and not ſolydat, yf the fyſſhe be faſte and ſolydat the yonger the fyſſhe is, the better it is to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt: but this is to vnderſtande, that yf the fyſſhe be neuer ſo ſolydat it muſte haue age / but not ouergrowen: except it be a yonge por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſſe the which kynde of fiſſhe is nother pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyd in the olde teſtament nor in phyſycke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Freſſhe water fyſſhe.</head>
                  <p>¶ The fyſſhe the whiche is in ryuers and bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes be more holſomer, than they the which be in pooles, pondes, or mootꝭ, or any other ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge water, for they doth laboure and doth ſkower them ſelfe. Fyſſhe the whiche lyueth &amp; doth feede on the moude, or els do feede in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fen or moryſſhe grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de doth ſauer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de whiche is not ſo good as the fyſſhe that fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyth and doth ſkowre them ſelf on the ſtones or grauell or ſande.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Salte fyſſhe.</head>
                  <p>¶ Salte fyſſhe the whiche be powderyd and ſalted with ſalte, be not greatly to be prayſed ſpecyally yf a man do make his hoole refecty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:16817:32"/> with it the qualyte doth not hurte, but the quantyte, ſpecyally ſuch ſalte fyſſhes as wyll cleue to the fyngers whan a man doth eate it And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkyn of fyſſhes be vtterly to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd, for it doth ingender vyſeus fleume and color aduſt. Al maner of fyſſhe is colde of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, and doth ingender fleume, it doth lytell nowryſſhe / Fyſſhe and fleſſhe oughte not to be eaten togyther at one meale.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xv. Chapitre, treateth of wylde fowle, and tame fowle byrdes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F al wylde fou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le, the Feſaunt is moſt beſte: Althoughe that a partreche of all fowles is ſooneſt dygeſted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherfore it is a reſtora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyue meate, and dothe comforte the brayne and the ſtomacke: &amp; doth augment carnall luſt. A wood cocke is a mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of good temperaunce. Quayles &amp; plouers and lapwynges doth nowryſſhe but lytel, for they doth ingender mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>coly humours, yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge turtyll doues dothe ingender good blode.
<pb facs="tcp:16817:33"/> A crane is harde of dygeſtyon, and doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der euyll blode. A yonge herenſew is lygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of dygeſtyon than a crane. A buſtarde well kylled and orderyd is a nutrytyue meate A byttoure is not ſo harde of dygeſtyon as is an herenſew. A ſhoueler is lyghter of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtyon than a byttoure, all theſe be noyfull except they be well orderyd and dreſſyd. A fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt henne. A more cocke and a more henne except they be ſutt abrode they be nutrytyue All maner of wylde fowle the whiche lyueth by the water they be of dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhement.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of tame or domeſtycall fowle.</head>
                  <p>¶ Of all tame fowle a capon is moſte beſte. For it is nutrytyue and is ſoone dygeſtyd. A henne in wynter is good and nutrytyue. And ſo is a chyken in ſomer, ſpecyallye coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>krellys and polettes, the whiche be vntroden. The fleſſhe of a cocke is harde of dygeſtyon: but the broth or gely made of a cocke is reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyue, pygyons be good for coloryke &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancoly men, goſe fleſſhe and ducke fleſſhe is not prayſed except it be a yonge grene gooſe yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge peechyken of halfe a yere of age be pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, olde pecockes be harde of dygeſtyon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Byrdes.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:33"/>
                  <p>¶ All maner of ſmale Byrdes, be good and lyght of dygeſtyon, except ſparowes whiche be harde of dygeſtyon, Tytmoſes, colmoſes and wrens, the whiche doth eate ſpyders and poyſon be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable, of all ſmale byrdes the larke is beſte: than is prayſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blacke byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; the thruſſhe. Raſis and Iſaac prayſeth yonge ſtaares, but I do thynke bycauſe they be bytter in etyng, they ſhuld inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der colour.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xvi. Chapytre, treatyth of fleſſhe, of wylde and tame beeſtes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eefe is a good me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate for an Englyſſhe man, ſo be it the beeſt be yonge, &amp; that it be not kowe fleſſhe. For olde beef and kowe fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe doth ingender melancolye and leporouſe humoures: yf it be moderatly powderyd that the grooſe blode by ſalte may be exhauſtyd, it doth make an Englyſſhe man ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion of hym with it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderyd. Martylmas beef whiche is called hanged beef in the rofe of the ſmoky howſe is not laudable, it maye fyll the bely and cauſe a man to drynke, but
<pb facs="tcp:16817:34"/> it is euyll for the ſtone, and euyll of dygeſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and maketh no good iuce. If a man haue a peace hangynge by his ſyde and another in his bely, that the whiche doth hange by the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſhall do hym more good yf a ſhowre of ray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne do chaunſe: than that the which is in his be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, the appetyde of mans ſenſualyte notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Veale.</head>
                  <p>¶ Veale is nutrytyue meate: and doth now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe moche a man, for it is ſoone dygeſtyd wherupon many men doth holde oppynyon that it is the beſte fleſſe and the moſte nutry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue meate that can be for mans ſuſtenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Mutton and lambe.</head>
                  <p>¶ Mutton of Raſis and Aueroyes, is pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed for a good meate, but Galen dothe not laude it, and ſewrely I do not loue it conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng that there is no beeſt that is ſo ſoone infectyd: nor there doth happen ſo great mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren and ſyckenes to any quadrypedyd beeſte as doth fall to the ſheepe. This notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, yf the ſheepe be brought vp in a good paſture and fatte and do not flauoure of the wolle it is good for ſycke perſons, for it doth ingender good blode.</p>
                  <p>¶ Lambes fleſſhe is moyſte and flumatycke
<pb facs="tcp:16817:34"/> wherfore it is not all the beſt for olde men, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepte they be melancolye of complexyon, it is not good for flumatyke men to feade to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of it doth hurte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Porke browne, bakon, &amp; pygge.</head>
                  <p>¶ where as Galen with other auncyent and approbat doctours doth prayſe porke I dare not ſay the contrarye agaynſt them, but this I am ſure of, I dyd neuer loue it: And in ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcrypture it is not prayſed, for a ſwyne is an vnclene beeſt and dothe lye vpon fylthy &amp; ſtynkynge ſoyles, and with ſtercorus matter dyuers tymes doth fede in Englande, yet in Hyghalmen and other hygh countres except (ſpayne &amp; other countres anexed to ſpayne) doth kepe theyr ſwyne clene, and dothe cauſe them ones or twyſe a day to ſwym<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in great ryuers, lyke the water of Ryne, whiche is abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue Coleyne, but ſpaynyerdes with the other regions anexed to them, kepe the ſwyne more fylthyer than englyſſe perſons doth. Further more the Ieue, the Saraſon, the Turkes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſernynge theyr polytycke wyt and lerenyng in phyſycke, hath as moche wyt, wyſdom, rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, and knowlege for the ſauyte of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: as any chryſten man hath, and noble phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycyons, I haue knowen amonges them: yet
<pb facs="tcp:16817:35"/> they all lacked grace, for as moche as they do not knowe or knowledge Ieſu chryſte, as the holy ſcrypture tellyth vs and them. They lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyth not porke nor ſwynes fleſſe, but doth vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuperat &amp; abhorre it, yet for all this they wyll rate adders, whiche is a kynde of ſerpentes, as well as any other cryſten man dwellynge in Rome, &amp; other hyghe countres, for adders fleſſhe there is called fyſſhe of the mountayn This notwithſtandynge phyſycke dothe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probat adders fleſſhe good to be eaten, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge it dothe make an olde man yonge, as it apperyth by a harte eatyng an adder makyth hym yonge agayne. But porke doth not ſo, for yf it be of an olde hogge not clene kepte it doth ingender groſe blode, &amp; doth humect to moche the ſtomacke, yet yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> porke be yon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge it is nutrytyue.</p>
                  <p>¶ Bacon is good for carters and plowmen, the whiche be euer labourynge in the earth or dunge, but &amp; yf they haue the ſtone and vſe to eate it they ſhall ſynge wo be the pye: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I do ſay that coloppes and egges, is as holſome for them: as a talowe candell is good for a horſe mouth, or a peeſe of powdred beef is good for a blereyed mare, yet ſenſuall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petyde muſt haue a ſwynge, all theſe thinges
<pb facs="tcp:16817:35"/> withandynge, porke is conuertyble to mans fleſſhe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Brawne.</head>
                  <p>¶ Brawne is an vſual meate in wynter amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges Englyſſhe men, it is harde of dygeſtyon the brawne of a wylde boore, is moche more better than the brawne of a tame boore, yf a man eate nother of them bothe it ſhall neuer do hym harme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Pygges.</head>
                  <p>¶ Pygges ſpecyally ſowe pygges is nutryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyue and made in a gelye, it is reſtoratyue ſo be it the pygge be fleed the ſkyn taken of, and than ſtewed with reſtoratyues, as a cocke is ſtewed to make a gely. A yonge fatte pygge in phyſicke is ſyngulerly prayſed yf it be wel orderyd in the roſtynge, the ſkyn not eaten.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Kydde.</head>
                  <p>¶ Yonge Kyddes fleſſhe is prayſed aboue all other fleſſhe, as Auicen, Raſis, &amp; Aueroyes ſayth, for it is temperate and nutrytyue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be ſomwhat dry. Olde kydde is not prayſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of wylde beeſtes fleſſhe.</head>
                  <p>¶ I haue gone rownde aboute cryſtendome and ouertwharte cryſtendom, &amp; a thouſande or two and more myles out of cryſtendom,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:36"/> yet there is not ſo moche pleaſure for harte &amp; hynde, bucke, and doo: and for roo bucke and doo, as is in Englande, &amp; although the fleſſhe be diſprayſed in phyſycke / I pray god to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de me part of the fleſſhe to eate phyſycke not withſtandyng. The opynyon of all olde phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſycyons was &amp; is that venyſon is not good to eate pryncipaylly for two cauſe, the fyrſte cauſe is that the beeſt doth lyue in fere: for yf he be a good wood man, he ſhall neuer ſe no kynde of deere, but at the .x. byt on the graſſe, or broſynge on the tree, but he wyll lyfte vp his hed &amp; loke aboute hym, the whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of tymoryſnes, and tymoroſyte doth brynge in melancoly humours. wherfore all Phyon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuchons ſayth that venyſon which is the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de cauſe doth ingender coloryke humours &amp; of trueth it doth ſo: wherfore let them take the ſkyn and let me haue the fleſſhe, I am ſure it is a lordes dyſſhe, and I am ſure it is good for an Englyſſhe man, for it doth anymate hym to be as he is: whiche is ſtronge and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / but I do aduertyſe euery man for all my wordes not to kyll and ſo to eate of it except it be lefully, for it is a meate for great men. And great men do not ſet ſo moch by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te as they do by the paſtyme of kyllyng of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:36"/>
                  <head>¶ Of Hares fleſſhe.</head>
                  <p>¶ A hare doth no harme nor dyſpleaſure to no man, yf the fleſſhe be not eaten, it maketh a gentylman good paſtyme. And better it is for the houndꝭ or dogges to eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hare after they haue kylled it, as I ſayd than man ſhuld eate it: for it is not prayſed nother in the olde Teſtament nother in phyſycke, for the byble ſayth the hare is an vnclene beeſte. And phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycke ſayeth hares fleſſhe is drye and doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender melancoly humours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Conys fleſſhe.</head>
                  <p>¶ Conys fleſſhe is good, but rabettes fleſſhe is beſte of al wylde beeſtes / for it is temperat and doth nowryſſhe, and ſyngulerly prayſed in phyſycke, for all thynges the whiche dothe ſucke is nutrytyue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xvij. Chapytre, doth treate of pertyculer thynges, of fyſſhe and fleſſhe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He heddes of fyſſhe, and the fatnes of fyſſhe ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally of Samon and Conger is not good for them the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be dyſpoſed to haue rew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matycke heddes. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heddes of lampryes,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:37"/> &amp; lamprons, &amp; the ſtrynge the whiche is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theym, is not good to eate refrayne from etynge of the kynnes of fyſſhe, and fleſſhe &amp; bornet meate, and browne meate, for it doth ingender viſcus humours, and color &amp; melan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coly. And doth make opylacions. The bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any beeſt is not laudable, excepte the brayne of a kydde, for it is euyl of digeſtyon and doth hurte a mans appetyde and the ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke, for it is colde and moyſte, and viſcus a hote ſtomacke may eate it, but it doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der groſe humours. The brayne of a wodco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cke and of a ſnype and ſuche lyke is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The foreparte of all maner of beeſtes &amp; fowles be more hotter and lyghter of digeſty on, than the hynder partes be. The marye of all beeſtes is hote and moyſte, it is nutrityue yf it be wel dygeſtyd, yet it doth mollyfy the ſtomacke, and doth take away a mans appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyde. wherfore let a man eate peper with it. The blode of all beeſtes &amp; fowles is not pray fed, for it is hard of digeſtyon. All y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inwardꝭ of beeſtes and of fowles, as the herte the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the lunges, and trypes, and trylybubbes: with all the intrayles is harde of dygeſtyon, and doth increaſe groſe humoures. The fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of fleſſhe is not ſo moche nutrytyue as
<pb facs="tcp:16817:37"/> the leenes of fleſſhe, it is beſt whan leene and fat is myxte one with another. The tunges of beeſtes be harde of dygeſtyon and of lytell nowryſſhement. The ſtones of a cockrell, &amp; the ſtones of other beeſtes that hath not done theyr kynde be nutrytyue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xviij. Chapitre, treatyth of roſte meate, of fryed meate and of bake meate.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith vs at Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pylour, and other vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyties is vſed boyled mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te at dyner, and roſte mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te to ſupper: why they ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de do ſo I can not tell on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be for a conſuetude. For boyled meate is lyghter of digeſtyon than roſted meate is. Bruled meate is harde of digeſtyon, &amp; euyll for the ſtone. Fryed meate is harder of dyge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton than brulyd meate is, and it doth ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der color and melancoly: Bake meate which is called fleſſhe that is beryd, for it is buryd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paaſt, is not prayſed in phyſycke. All maner of fleſſhe the which is inclyned to humydyte ſhulde be roſtyd. And all fleſſhe the whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:16817:38"/> inclyned to drynes ſhulde be ſodde or boyled. ¶ Fyſſhe may be ſod, roſtyd, brulyd &amp; baken, euery one after theyr kynde, and vſe &amp; faſſhy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the countree, as the coke and the phyſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon wyll agre and deuyſe. For a good coke is halfe a phyſycyon. For the chefe phyſycke (the counceyll of a phyſycyon excepte) dothe come from the kytchyn, wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phyſycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the coke for ſycke men muſte conſult togyther for the preparacion of meate for ſyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke men. For yf the phyſycyon without the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke prepare any meate excepte he be very ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pert, he wyll make a weryſſe dyſſhe of meate, the whiche the ſycke can not take.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xix. Chapitre, treateth of Roo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and fyrſte of the rootes borage, and of bugloſſe.</head>
               <p>THe rootes of Borage and Bugloſſe ſoden tender and made in a ſuccade, doth ingender good blode, and doth ſet a man in atemporaunce.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ The rootes of Alyſaunder and Enulacampana.</head>
                  <p>¶ The rootes of Alyſaunder ſoden tender, and made in ſuccade is good for to dyſtroy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſtone in the Raynes of the backe &amp; blader
<pb facs="tcp:16817:38"/> The rootes of Enulacampana ſoden tender and made in a ſuccade is good for the breſte, and for the lunges, and for all the interyall membres of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ The rootes of percelly, &amp; of fenell.</head>
                  <p>¶ The Rootes of percelly ſoden tender and made in a ſuccade is good for the ſtone, and doth make a man to pyſſe. The rootes of Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nell ſoden tender &amp; made in a ſuccade is good for the lunges and for the ſyght.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ The rootes of turnepes &amp; perſnepes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Turnepes boyled and eaten with fleſſhe, augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyth the ſeede of man, yf they be eaten rawe moderatly, it doth prouoke a good ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyde. Perſnepes ſoden &amp; eaten doth increaſe nature, they be nutrityue, &amp; doth expell vryne</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Radyſſhe rootes, and Caretes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Radyſſhe rootes doth breke wynde &amp; dothe prouoke a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make water, but they be not good for them the whiche hath the gowte. Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retes ſoden and eaten dothe auge &amp; increaſe nature &amp; doth cauſe a man to make water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ The rootes of Rapes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Rape rootes yf they be well boyled they do nowryſſhe, yf they be moderatly eaten, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly eaten they doth ingender ventoſyte, and doth anoye the ſtomacke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:39"/>
                  <head>¶ Of Onyons.</head>
                  <p>¶ Onyons doth prouoke a man to venery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actes, and to ſompuolence, &amp; yf a man drynke ſondry drynkes it doth rectyfy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the varyete of the operacyon of them: they maketh a mans apetyde good, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth away faſtydyouſnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Leekes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Leekes doth open the breſte, and doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke a man to make water, but they doth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke and increaſe euyll blode.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Garlyke.</head>
                  <p>¶ Garlyke of all rootes is vſed &amp; moſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Lombardy, and other countres anexed to it, for it doth open the breſte, &amp; it doth kyll all maner of wormes in a mans bely, whiche be to ſay, lumbrici, aſcarides, and cucurbitini whiche is to ſaye longe wormes, ſmall lytell longe wormes whiche wyll tykle in the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and ſquare wormes: it alſo hetyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and deſoluyth groſe wyndes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xx. Chapitre, treateth of vſuall Herbes. And fyrſte of Borage, and Bugloſſe.</head>
               <p>BOrage doth comforte the herte, and doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der good blode, and
<pb facs="tcp:16817:39"/> cauſeth a man to be mery, &amp; doth ſet a man in temporaunce. And ſo doth bugloſſe for he is taken of more vygor &amp; ſtrength &amp; effycacye.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Artochockes, and Rokat.</head>
                  <p>¶ There is nothynge vſed to be eaten of Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tochockes but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed of them, whan they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rype they muſt be ſoden te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broth of heef, &amp; after eate them at dyner, they doth increaſe nature, and dothe prouoke a man to beneryous actes. Rokat doth increaſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of man, and doth ſtumulat the fleſſhe, and doth helpe to dygeſtyon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Cykory, and Endyue.</head>
                  <p>¶ Cykory doth kepe the ſtomacke and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heed in temporaunce, and doth qualyfy color. En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyue is good for them the whiche haue hoote ſtomackes and drye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of whyte Beetes, and Purſlane.</head>
                  <p>¶ whyte Beetes be good for the lyuer, &amp; for the ſplene, and be abſterſyue. Purſlane dothe extynct the ardor of laſſyuyouſnes, and doth mytygate great heate in all the inwarde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Tyme, and Parſley.</head>
                  <p>¶ Tyme brekyth the ſtone, it dothe deſolue wyndes. And cauſeth a man to make water. Parſley is good to breake the ſtone, and cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:16817:40"/> a man to pyſſe, it is good for the ſtomac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke, &amp; doth cauſe a man to haue a ſwete breth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Lettyſe, and Sorell.</head>
                  <p>Lettyſe doth extynct veneryous actes, yet it doth increaſe mylke in a womans breſte, it is good for a hote ſtomacke, and doth prouoke ſlepe, and doth increaſe blod, and doth ſet the blode in a temporaunce. Sorell is good for a hote lyuer, and good for the ſtomacke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Penyryall, and Iſope.</head>
                  <p>¶ Penyryall doth purge mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>coly, and doth comforte the ſtomacke &amp; the ſpyrites of man. Iſope clenſeth viſcus fleume, &amp; is good for the breſte and for the lunges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Rooſmary, and Roſes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Rooſmary is good for palſes, and for the fallynge ſyckenes, and for the cowghe, and good agaynſt colde. Roſes be a cordyall and doth comforte the herte &amp; the brayne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Fenell, and Anys.</head>
                  <p>¶ Theſe herbes be ſeldome vſed, but theyr ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be greatly occupyde. Fenell ſede is vſed to breke wynde, and good agaynſt poyſon. Anys ſede is good to clenſe the bladder, and the raynes of the backe: &amp; doth prouoke vryne and maketh one to haue a ſoote breth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Sawge, and Mandragod.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:40"/>
                  <p>¶ Sawge is good to helpe a woman to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue, and doth prouoke vryne. Mandragor doth helpe a woman to concepcion, and doth prouoke a man to ſlepe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of all herbes ingenerall.</head>
                  <p>¶ There is no Herbe, nor weede, but god ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue gyuen vertue to them, to helpe man. But for as moche, as Plyne, Macer, and Diaſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rides with many other olde auncyent and ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>probat Doctours hath wrytten and pertrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of theyr vertues, I therfore nowe wyll wryte no further of herbes, but wyll ſpeke of other matters that ſhalbe more neceſſarye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxi. Chapitre, treatyth of Fruytes, and fyrſte of Fygges.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vicen ſayth that Fygges doth nowryſſhe mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re than any other Fruyte, they doth nowryſſhe merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſlye, whan they be eaten with blanched Almons. They be alſo good roſted, &amp; ſtued. They do clenſe the breſt &amp; the lunges, &amp; they do open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opylacyons of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yuer &amp; the ſplene. They doth ſtere a man to
<pb facs="tcp:16817:41"/> veneryous actes, for they doth auge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the ſede of generacyon. And alſo they doth prouoke a man to ſweate: wherfore they doth ingender lyce.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of great Rayſyns.</head>
                  <p>¶ Great Rayſyns be nutrytyue ſpecially yf the ſtones be pullyd out. And they doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the ſtomacke fyrme &amp; ſtable. And they doth prouoke a man to haue a good appetyde, yf a fewe of them be eaten before meate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of ſmale Rayſyns of Corans.</head>
                  <p>¶ ſmale rayſyns of Corans, be good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raynes of the backe, and they dothe prouoke vryne. Howbeit they be not all the beſt for the ſplene, for they maketh opylacyon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Grapes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Grapes ſwete and newe, be nutrytyue, &amp; and doth ſtumulat the fleſſhe. And they doth comforte the ſtomacke and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuer, and doth auoyde opylacyons. Howbeit, it doth replete the ſtomacke with ventoſyte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Peches, of Medlers, &amp; Ceruyces.</head>
                  <p>¶ Peches doeth mollyfy the bely and be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, Medlers taken ſuperfluous dothe ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der melancolye. And Ceruyces be in maner of lyke operacyon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Strawburyes, Cherys, &amp; Hurtes.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:41"/>
                  <p>¶ Strawburyes, be prayſed aboue al buryes for they do qualyfye the heate of the lyuer, &amp; dothe ingender good blode eaten with ſuger. Cherys doth mollyfye the bely and be colde. Hurtes be of a groſer ſubſtaunce. wherfore they be not for them the whiche be of a clene dyete.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Nuttes great and ſmale.</head>
                  <p>¶ The walnut &amp; the banocke be of one opera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon. They be tarde and ſlowe of digeſtyon, yet they doth comforte the brayne if the pyth or ſkyn be pylled of, and than they be nutry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue. Fylberdes be better than haſell Nuttes: yf they be newe and taken from the tree, and the ſkyn or the pyth pullyd of, they be nutry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue, &amp; doth increaſe fatnes, yf they be olde they ſhuld be eaten with great rayſens. But new nuttes be farre better than olde nuttes, for olde nuttes be colorycke, and they be cuyl for the hed and euyll for olde men. And they dothe ingender the palſey to the tounge, yet they be good agaynſt venym. And immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly taken or eaten doth ingender corrupcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as byles blaynes &amp; ſuche putryfaction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Peaſon, and Beanes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Peaſon the whiche be yonge be nutrytyue Howbeit they doth replete a man with vento<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte.
<pb facs="tcp:16817:42"/> Beanes be not ſo moche to be prayſed as peaſon, for they be full of ventoſyte altho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughe the ſkynnes or huſkes be ablatyd or caſt away, yet they be a ſtronge meate, and dothe prouoke veneryous actes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Peares, and Appulles.</head>
                  <p>¶ Peares the whiche be melow and doulce &amp; not ſtony doth increaſe fatnes ingenderyng wateryſſhe blod. And they be ful of ventoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. But wardens roſted ſtued, or baken be nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trytyne, and doth comforte the ſtomacke ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyally yf they be eaten with comfettes. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples be good after a froſt haue taken them or whan they be olde, ſpecyally red apples, and they the which be of good odor &amp; melow, they ſhuld be eaten with ſuger or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fettes, or with fenell ſede, or anye ſede bycauſe of theyr ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toſyte, they doth comforte than the ſtomacke and doth make good dygeſtyon, ſpecyally yf they be roſtyd or baken.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Pomegranates, &amp; Quynces.</head>
                  <p>¶ Pomegranates be nutrytyue, and good for the ſtomacke. Quinces baken the core pul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led out doth mollyfy the bely, and doth helpe dygeſtyon, and dothe preſerue a man from dronkenſhyppe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Daates, and Mylons.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16817:42"/>
                  <p>¶ Daates moderatly eaten be nutrityue but they doth cauſe opylacyons of the lyuer and of the ſplene. Mylons doth ingender euyl hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of gourdes, of Cucubres, &amp; pepones.</head>
                  <p>¶ Gourdes be euyll of nowryſſhement, Cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, reſtrayneth veneryouſnes or laſſyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, or luxuryouſnes. Pepones be in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lyke operacion: but the pepones ingen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deryng euyll humours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Almondes, and Chefteyns.</head>
                  <p>¶ Almondes cauſeth a man to pyſſe: they do mollyfy the bely, and doth purge the lunges. And .vi. or .vii. eate before meate preſerueth a man from dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenſhyp. Cheſteynes doth now<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſhe the body ſtrongly, &amp; doth make a man fat, yf they be thorowe roſted and the huſkes abiected, yet they doth replete a man with ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toſyte or wynde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Prunes, and Damyſens.</head>
                  <p>¶ Prunes be nat greatly prayſed, but in the way of medyſyne, for they be cold &amp; moyſte. And Damyſens be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd nature: for the one is olde and dryed, and the other be taken from the tre .vi. or .vii. damyſens eaten before dyner be good to prouoke a mans appetyde, they doth mollyfy the bely and be abſterſyues
<pb facs="tcp:16817:43"/> the ſkyn and the ſtones muſte be ablatyd and caſte awaye and not vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Olyues, and Capers.</head>
                  <p>¶ Olyues condyted, and eaten at the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge of refectyon doth corroborate the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and prouoketh appetyde. Capers doth purge fleume, and doth make a man to haue an appetyde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Orenges.</head>
                  <p>¶ Orenges doth make a man to haue a good appetyde, and ſo doth the ryndes, yf they be in ſuccade, &amp; they doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the ſtomacke, the Iuce is a good ſauce and dothe prouoke an appetyde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxij. Chapitre, treateth of ſpyces, and fyrſte of Gynger.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ynger doth hete the ſtomacke and helpyth dygeſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, grenegynger eaten in the moreni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge faſtynge doth acuat and quycken the remembraunce.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Peper.</head>
                  <p>¶ There be .iii. ſondry kyndꝭ of peper, which be to ſay whyte Peper, blacke Peper, &amp; long Peper. All kyndes of pepers to heate the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:16817:43"/> and doth deſolue fleume &amp; wynde &amp; dothe helpe dygeſtyon, and maketh a man to make water. Blacke peper doth make a man leane.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Cloues, and Mace.</head>
                  <p>¶ Cloues doth comforte the ſenewes, &amp; doth dyſolue, and doth conſume ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, reſtoryth nature. Maces is a cordyall and doth helpe the colycke: &amp; is good agaynſt the blody flyxe and laxes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Graynes, and Safferon.</head>
                  <p>¶ Graynes be good for the ſtomake and the hed. And be good for women to drynke. Saf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feron doth comforte the herte &amp; the ſtomacke but he is to hote for the lyuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Nutmeges, &amp; Cynomome.</head>
                  <p>¶ Nutmeges be good for them the whiche ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue colde in theyr hed, and dothe comforte the ſyght and the brayne &amp; the mouthe of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, &amp; is good for the ſplene. Cynomome is a cordyall, wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrecyon doth ſay why doth a man dye &amp; can gette Cynomome to eate: yet it doth ſtop &amp; is good to reſtrayne fluxes or laxes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Lyqueryce.</head>
                  <p>¶ Lyqueryce is good to clenſe and to open the lunges &amp; the breſt, &amp; doth looſe fleume.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxiij. Chapytre, ſheweth a dyete for Sanguyne men.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:44"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Anguyne men be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hoote and moyſte of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, wherfor they muſt be cyrcumſpect in eatynge of theyr meate, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that the purer the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexon is, the ſoner it may be coruptyd, &amp; the blode maye be the ſooner infectyd / wherfore they muſt abſtayne to eate inordynatly fruy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and herbes and rotes, as garlyke onyons and leekes, they muſt refrayne from eatyng of olde fleſſhe, and exchew the vſage of etyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the braynes of beeſtes: &amp; from etynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vdders of keyn. They muſte vſe moderat ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, and moderat dyet or els they wyl be to fat and groſe. Fyſſhe of muddy waters be not good for them. And yf blode do abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe it with ſtufes, or by fleubothomye,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxiiij. Chapyter ſheweth a dyete for Fleumatyke men.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Leumaticke men be colde and moyſte: wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re they muſt abſtayne from meates, the whiche is colde. And alſo they muſt refray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from eatyng viſcus meate, ſpecially from
<pb facs="tcp:16817:44"/> all meates the whiche doth ingender fleuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycke humours, as fyſſhe, fruyte, and whyte meate. Alſo to exchewe the vſage of eatynge of crude herbes ſpecyall to refrayne from me ate the whiche is harde and ſlowe of dygeſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on: as it appereth in the propertes of meates aboue reherſyd. And to beware not to dwell nyghe to wateryſſhe and moryſſhe grounde. Theſe thynges be good for fleumatycke per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons moderatly taken, onyons, garlycke, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, gynger. And all meates the whiche be ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and drye. And ſauces the whiche be ſowre. Theſe thyngꝭ folowyng doth purge fleume polypody, netyll, elder, agarycke, yreos, may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den heere, and ſtycados.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxv. Chapitre, ſheweth a dyete for Colorycke men.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Olor is hote and dry wherfore Coloryke men muſte abſtayne from eatyng hote ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to refrayne from dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge of wyne, and eatynge of Colorycke meate: howbeit Colorycke men may eate gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſer meate than any other of complexions, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept theyr educacion haue ben to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary.
<pb facs="tcp:16817:45"/> Colorycke me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde not be longe faſtynge. Theſe thyngꝭ folowyng do purge color: Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytory Centory, wormewod, wylde hoppes vyoletes, Mercury, Manna, Reuberbe, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patory, Tamarindes, &amp; the whay of butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxvi. Chapitre treateth of a dyetarye, for Melancoly men.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Elancoly is colde &amp; drye, wherfore Melancoly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt refrayne from fryed me ate, and meate the whiche is ouer ſalte. And from meate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſowre &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of dygeſtyon, and from all meate the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is burnet and drye. They muſt abſtayne from immoderat thurſte, and from drinkyng of hote wynes, and groſe wyne as red wyne And vſe theſe thynges Cowe mylke, Almon mylke, yolkes of rere egges. Boyled meate is better for Melancoly men than roſted meate All meate the which wylbe ſoone dygeſtyd, &amp; all meates the which doth ingender good blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. And meates the whiche be temperatly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te be good for Melancoly men. And ſo be all herbes the whiche be hote and moyſte. Theſe thynges folowynge doth purge Melancoly,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:45"/> quyckbeme, Seene, ſticados, hartyſtounge, mayden heere, pulyall mountane, borage, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganum, ſuger, and whyte wyne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxvij. Chapiter, treatyth of a dyete, and of an ordre to be vſed in the Peſtyferous tyme of the peſtylence &amp; ſwetyng ſycknes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the Plages of the Peſtylence, or the ſwetynge ſyckenes is in a towne, or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree, with vs at Mountpylour, and all other hygh Regyons and countrees y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue dwelt in, the people doth fle from the contagious and infectious ayre preſeruatyues with other counceyll of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycke notwithſtandyng. In lower and other baaſe countres, howſes the which be infectyd in towne or cytie, be cloſyd vp both doores &amp; wyndowes: &amp; the inhabytours ſhall not come a brode, nother to churche: nor to market, nor to any howſe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, for infectyng other the which be clene without infection. A man can not be to ware: nor can not kepe hym ſelf to well from this ſyckenes, for it is ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:16817:46"/> and ſo parlouſe, that the ſyckenes is ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauour of a mans clothes the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath vyſyted the infectious howſe, for the infection wyl lye and hange longe in clothes And I haue knowen that whan the ſtrawe &amp; ruſſhes hath ben caſt out of a howſe infectyd the hogges the whiche dyd lye in it, dyed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtylence: wherfore in ſuch infectious tyme it is good for euery man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyl not flye from the contagyous ayre to vſe dayly, ſpecyally in the mornynge and euenyng to burne Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neper, or Roſemary, or Ryſſhes, or Gaye le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or Maierome, or Francke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, bengauyn. Or els make this powder. Take of ſtorax ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamyte half an vnce, of frankenſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce an vnce, of the wodde of Aloes, the weyghte of .vi. d. myxe all theſe togyther. Than caſt half a ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefull of this in a chaffyngdyſſhe of coles. And ſet it to fume abrode in the chambers, &amp; the hall, and other howſes. And you wyll put to this powder a lytell Lapdanum: it is ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better. Or els make a pomemau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this maner. Take of Lapdanum .iii. dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wodde of Aloes one drame, of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of grece .ii. drames, and a half, of nutmeg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, of ſtorax calamite of eche a drame and a half, confect all theſe togyther with Roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:16817:46"/> &amp; make a ball. And this aforeſayd Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder doth not onely expell contagyous ayre, but alſo it doth comforte the brayne, as Barthelmew of Montagnaue ſayth, &amp; other modernall doctors doth afferme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: who ſo euer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is infectyd with the peſtylence / let hym loke in my breuyary of helth for a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. But let hym vſe this dyete, let the Cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber be kept cloſe. And kepe a contynuall fyre in the Chamber of clere burnynge wodde, or chare cole without ſmoke, beware of takynge any colde, vſe temporat meates and drynke, and beware of wyne, bere, &amp; cyder, vſe to eate ſtued or baken wardens yf they can begoten yf not eate ſtued or baken peers with comfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, vſe no groſe meates, but thoſe the whiche be lyght of dygeſtyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxviij. Chapitre, ſheweth of a dyete, the whiche be in any Feuer or agew.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do aduertyſe euery man that hath a Feuer: or an A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gewe, not to eate no meate .vi. houres before his courſe doth take hym. And
<pb facs="tcp:16817:47"/> in no wyſe as longe as the Agew doth indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, to put of ſhertte nor dowblet, nor to ryſe out of the bedde, but whan nede ſhall requyre and in any wyſe not to go, nor to take any open ayer. For ſuche prouyſyon may be had that at vttermoſt at the thyrde courſe he ſhall be delyuered of the Feuer vſynge the medſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the whiche be in the Breuyary of helthe. And let euery man beware of caſtynge theyr handes &amp; armes at any tyme out of the bed, in or out of theyr agony, or to ſpraule with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> legges out of the bed, good it is for the ſpace of .iii. courſes to weare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewelly gloues, and not to waſſhe the handes. And to vſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a dyete in meate &amp; drynke as is reherſyd in the peſtylence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxix. Cpapitre, treatyth of a dyete for them, the whiche haue the Iliacke, or the colyck, &amp; the ſtone.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Iliacke and the Colycke be ingendered of ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toſyte, the whiche is intruſyd, or incloſed in two guttes, the one is called Ilia. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other is called Colon. For theſe two infyrmytes a
<pb facs="tcp:16817:47"/> man muſte beware of colde. And good it is not to be longe faſtynge. And neceſſary it is to be laxatyue and not in no wyſe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtupat. And theſe thynges folowyng be not good for them the which haue theſe aforeſaid infyrmytꝭ, new bred, ſtale bred, nor new ale. They muſt abſtayne alſo from drynkyng of beere, of cyder, and red wyne, and cynamom Alſo refrayne from al meates that ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny is in exchew eatyng of cold herbes, vſe not to eate beanes, peſon, nor potage, beware of the vſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of fruytes. And of all thynges the whiche doth ingender wynde. For the ſtone abſtayn from drynkynge of new ale, beware of beere, and of red wyne, and hote wynes, refrayne from eatynge of red herynge, matylmas beef and bakon, and ſalte fyſſhe, and ſalt meates. And beware of goynge colde aboute the mydell ſpecyally aboute the raynes of the backe. And make no reſtryc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon, of wynde and water: nor ſeege that nature wolde expelle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxx. Chapitre, treatyth of a dyete for them the whiche haue any kyndes of the gowte.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:48"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey the whiche be infectyd with the gowte, or any kynde of it, I do aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe them not to ſyt long bol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge and bybbynge dyſyng and cardyng, in forgettyng them ſelfe to exonerat the blader and the bely whan nede ſhall requyre, and alſo to beware that the legges hange not without ſome ſtay nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bootꝭ or ſhoes be not ouer ſtrayte, who ſoeuer hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gowte muſt refrayne from drynkyng of newe ale, and let hym abſtayne from drynkyng of beere and red wyne, Alſo he muſt not eate new brede, egges, freſſhe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, eles, freſſhe heryng, pylcherdꝭ, oyſters: and all ſhell fyſſhe. Alſo he muſte exchew the eatynge of freſſhe beef, of gooſe, of ducke, &amp; of pygyons. Beware of takyng colde in the legge, or rydyng, or goynge wetſhod. Bewa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of veneryous actꝭ after refection, or after or vpon a full ſtomacke. And refrayne from all thinges that doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der euyll humours and be inflatyue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The, xxxi. Chapytre, treatyth of a dyete for them the whiche haue any of the kyndes of lypored.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:48"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that is infectyd, with any of the .iiii. kyndes of the lepored muſt refrayne from all maner of wynes, &amp; from new drynkes, and ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ale, than let hym beware of ryot and ſurfe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge. And let hym abſtayne from etyng of ſpyces, and daates, and from trypes &amp; podyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and all inwardes of beeſtes. Fyſſhe and egges, &amp; mylke is not good for leperous per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons: and they muſt abſtayne from eating of freſſhe beef, and from eatynge of goſe, ducke and from water fowle and pygions. And in no wyſe eate no veneſon, nor hare fleſſhe and ſuche lyke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxii. Thapytre, treatyth of a dyete for them, the whiche haue any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyndes of the fallyng ſyckenes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſo euer he be, the which haue any of the kyndes of the fallyng ſyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes muſt abſtayn from eatynge of whyte meate, ſpecially of milke he muſt
<pb facs="tcp:16817:49"/> refrayne from drynkyng of wyne, newe ale, and ſtronge ale. Alſo they ſhulde not eate the fatnes of fyſſhe, nor the hedes of fyſſhe, the whiche dothe ingender rewme. Shell fyſſhe, eles, ſamon, herynge, &amp; viſcus fyſſhes be not good for Epilentycke men. Alſo they muſte refrayne from eatynge of garlyke, onyons, leekes, chybbolles, and all vaperous meates, the whiche doth hurte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed: venſon, hare fleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe, beef, beanes, and peaſon be not good for Epilentycke men. And yf they knowe that they be infected with this great ſycknes, they ſhulde not reſorte where there is great reſorte of company, whiche is in churche in ſeſſyons and market places on market dayes, yf they do the ſycknes wyll infeſte them more there, than in any other place, or at any other tyme They muſt beware they do not ſyt to nyghe the fyre, for the fyre wyll ouercom them, and wyll induce the ſycknes. They muſt beware of lyeng hote in theyr bed, or to laboure extre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely, for ſuche thynges cauſyth the grefe to come the ofter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxiij. Chapytre, treatyth, of a dyete, the whiche haue any payne in the hed.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16817:49"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any ſycknes, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmytes and impedymentes may be in a mans hed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re who ſo euer haue any impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the hed muſt not ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe the hed to hote, nor to colde, but in a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraunce. And to beware of ingendryng of rewme, whiche is the cauſe of many infyrmy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. There is nothynge that dothe ingender rewme ſo moche as doth the fatnes of fyſſhe and the heddes of fyſſhe, and ſurfeſtes, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge colde in the feete: and takynge colde in the nape of the necke or hed. Alſo they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue any infyrmyte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed muſt refray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of immoderat ſlepe ſpecyally after meate Alſo they muſt abſtayne from drynkynge of wyne, and vſe not to drynke ale and beere the whiche is ouer ſtronge: vocyferacyon halow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, cryeng, and hygh ſynging is not good for the hed. All thynges the whiche is vapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous or dothe fume, is not good for the hed. And all thynges the which is of euyll ſauour as caryn, ſynkes, wyddrawghtes, piſſe bolles ſnoffe of candellys, dunghylles, ſtynkynge canellys, and ſtynkynge ſtandyng waters, &amp; ſtynkynge marſhes, with ſuche contagyous
<pb facs="tcp:16817:50"/> eyres doth hurte the hed and the brayne, and the memory. All odyferous ſauours be good for the hed and the brayne and the memory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxiiij. Chapitre, treateth of a dyete for them the whiche be in a conſumpcyon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſoeuer he be that is in a conſumpcyon muſte ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from all ſowre and tarte thynges as venegre &amp; alceger, &amp; ſuche lyke. And alſo he muſt abſtayne from eatynge of groſe meates the whiche be harde and ſlowe of dygeſtyon. And vſe cordyallys and reſtoratyues and nutrytyue meates. All meates and drinkes the which is ſwete &amp; that ſuger is in be nutrytyue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherfore ſwete wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be good for them the whiche be in conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion moderatly taken. And ſowre wyne, ſow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ale, and ſowre brede is good for no man. For it doth freate away nature, and let them beware that be in conſumpcion of fryde mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, of bruled meate, and bronte meate the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is ouer roſtyd. And in any wyſe let them beware of anger &amp; pencyfulnes. Theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges folowynge be good for them the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:16817:50"/> be in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumpcions a pygge or a cocke ſtewed and made in a gely, cockrellys ſtewed, gootꝭ mylke and ſuger, almon mylke in the whiche ryce is ſoden, and rabbetes ſtewed. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxv. Chapitre treateth of a dyete for them the whiche be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matyke men, beyng ſhort wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyd or lackynge breth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hortnes of wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth dyuers tymes, of impedymentꝭ in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſtraytnes of the breſt opylatyd thorow viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus fleume: and other why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le whan the hed is ſtuffyd with rewme called the poſe lettyth the breth of his naturall cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. wherfore he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſhortnes of breth: muſte abſtayne from eatyng of nuttes ſpecyally yf they be olde: cheſe and mylke is not good for them, no more is fyſſhe and feuyte, and rawe or crude herbes. Alſo all maner of meate, the whiche is harde of dygeſtion is not good for them. They muſte refrayne from eatyng of fyſſhe ſpecially from eatyng fyſſhe the which
<pb facs="tcp:16817:51"/> wyll cleue to the fyngers: &amp; be viſcus &amp; ſlyme &amp; in any wyſe beware of the ſkyns of fyſſhe &amp; of all maner of meate the whiche doth ingen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der fleume. Alſo they muſte beware of colde. And whan any howſe is a ſwepynge to go out of the howſe for a ſpace in to a clene eyre The duſt alſo that ryſeth in the ſtrete thorow the vehemens of the wynde or otherwyſe, is not good for theym. And ſmoke is euyll for them, and ſo is all thynge that is ſtoppynge. wherfor neceſſary it is for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be laxatyue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxvi. Cpapitre, treatyth of a dyete for them, the whiche haue the palſye.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey the whiche ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the Palſye, vnyuerſall, or pertyculer muſt beware of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, haſtynes, and teſtynes, &amp; muſt beware of feare, for tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row anger or feare dyuers tymes the Palſye do come to a man. Alſo they muſt beware of droke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, and eatyng of nuttes, whiche thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges be euyll for the palſye of the tonge, cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and contagyous, and ſtynkynge fylthy eyres be euyll for the palſye. And lette euery
<pb facs="tcp:16817:51"/> man beware on lyeng vpon the bare grounde or vpon the bare ſtones, for it is euyll for the Palſye, the ſauour of Caſtory, &amp; the ſauour of a fox is good agaynſt the palſye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxvij. Chapitre, doth ſhew an order and a dyete for them the whiche be madde, and out of theyr wytte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no man the whiche haue any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyndes of madnes: but they ought to be ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pte in ſauegarde for dyuers i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may fall, as it apperyd of late day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of a lunatycke man named Mychell, the whiche went many yeres at lyberte, &amp; at laſt he dyd kylle his wyfe and his wyfes ſuſter, &amp; his owne ſelfe. wherfore I do aduertyſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man the whiche is madde, or lunatycke or frantycke, or demonyacke to be kepte in ſaue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde, in ſome cloſe howſe or chamber, where there is lytell lyght. And that he haue a keper the whiche the madde man do feare. And ſe that the madde man haue no knyf nor ſheers nor other edge toule, nor that he haue no gyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyll
<pb facs="tcp:16817:52"/> except it be a week lyſte of clothe, for hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge or kyllynge hym ſelfe. Alſo the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or the howſe that the madde man is in, let there be no paynted clothes, nor paynted wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lys, nor pyctures of man nor woman or fow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le or beeſt: for ſuche thynges maketh them ful of fantaſyes, lette the madde perſons hed be ſhauen ones a moneth: let them drinke no wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne nor ſtronge ale, nor ſtronge beere, but mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derat drynke, and let them haue .iii. tymes in a daye warme ſuppynges, and lytell warme meate. And vſe few wordes to them, excepte it be for reprehenſyon, or gentyll reformacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yf they haue any wytte or perſeueraunce to vnderſtande.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxviij. Chapytre, treatyth of a dyete for them the whiche haue any of the kyndes of the Idropyſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynt Beede ſayeth the more a man doth drynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath the Idropiſe, the more he is a thurſt, for although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes doth come by ſuperabundaunce of wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, yet the lyuer is drye. whether it be alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:16817:52"/> Ipoſarca, Lencoflegmancia, or the tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. They that hath any of the .iiii. kyndes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idropyſes muſt refrayne from all thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges the whiche be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtupat and coſtyue, and vſe all thynges the which be laxatyue / nuttes and dry almondes and harde cheſe is poyſon to them. A ptyſane and poſſet ale made with colde herbes doth comforte them: who ſo euer he be, the whiche wyll haue a remedy for any of theſe foure kyndes of the Idropyſes, and wyll knowe a declaracyon of theſe infyrmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and all other ſyckneſſes, let hym loke in a boke of my makyng named the Breuyary of helth. For in this boke I do ſpeke but of dye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and how a man ſhuld order his manſyon place. And hym ſelf &amp; his bowſholde, with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyke thyngꝭ: for the conſeruacion of helth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xxxix. Chapytre, treateth of a generall dyete, for all maner of men and women, beynge ſycke or hole.</head>
               <p>THere is no man nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the which haue any reſpect to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe, that can be a better Pheſycion for theyr
<pb facs="tcp:16817:53"/> owne ſauegarde, than theyr owne ſelf can be to conſyder what thynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche doth them good. And to refrayne from ſuche thynges that doth them hurte or harme. And let euery man beware of care, ſorowe, thought, pency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and of inwarde anger. Beware of ſurfettes, and vſe not ſo moche veneryouſe actes. Brehe not the vſuall cuſtome of ſlepe in the nyght. A mery herte and mynde, the whiche is in reſte and quyetnes, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyte, and to moche worldly buſynes cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a man to lyue longe, and to loke yongly althoughe he be agyd, care and ſorowe bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in age and deth, where let euery man be mery: and yf he can not let hym reſorte to me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry company to breke of his perplexatyues. ¶ Furthermore I do aduertyſe euery man to waſſhe theyr handes ofte euery daye: And dyuers tymes to keyme theyr hed euery daye And to plounge the eyes in colde water in the morenyng. Moreouer I do councell eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry man to kepe the breſte and the ſtomacke warme. And to kepe the feete from wet, and other whyle to waſſhe them, and that they be not kept to hote nor to colde, but indyfferent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. Alſo to kepe the hed and the necke in a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derat temporaunce not to hote nor to colde,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:53"/> and in any wyſe to beware not to medle to moche with veneryous actꝭ: for that wyll cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe a man to loke agedly: &amp; alſo cauſeth a man to haue a breef or a ſhorte lyfe. All other mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters pertaynynge to any pertyculer dyete, you ſhall haue in the dyetes aboue in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke reherſyd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The .xl. Chapytre, doth ſhewe an order, or a faſſhyon, how a ſycke man ſhulde be ordered, And how a ſycke man ſhuld be vſyd that is lykely to dye.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoo ſo euer that is ſore ſycke, it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne to man, whether he ſhall lyue or dye. wherfore it is neceſſarye for hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſycke to haue two or .iii good kepers, the whiche at all tymes muſt be dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and not ſlepyſſhe ſloudgyſſhe, ſlut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſſhe. And not to wepe and wayle aboute a ſycke man, nor to vſe many wordes / nor that there be no great reſorte to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and talke,
<pb facs="tcp:16817:54"/> For it is a buſynes a whole man to anſwere many men, ſpecyally women that ſhall come to hym. They the which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to any ſycke perſon ought to haue few wordes or none: ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept certayne perſons the whiche be of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyll of the Teſtament makynge, the whiche wyſe men be not to ſeke of ſuche matters in theyr ſyckenes, for wyſdom wolde that euery man ſhulde prepare for ſuche thyngꝭ in helth And yf any man for charyte wyll vyſet any perſon, lette hym aduertyſe the ſycke to make euery thynge euyn bytwext god and the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence. And to receyue the ryghtꝭ of holy churche, lyke a catholycke man. And to folowe the counſeyll of both Phyſycyons whiche is to ſay the phyſycyon of the ſoule, &amp; the phyſycyon of the body, that is to ſaye the ſpyrituall counſeyl of his ghoſtly father, and the bodely counſeyll of his phyſycyon conſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng the receytes of his medſons to recouer helth. For ſaynt Auguſtyn ſaith he that doth not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of his phyſycyon doth kyll hym ſelf. Furthermore about a ſycke per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone ſhuld be redolent ſauour, and the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhuld be replenyſſhed with herbes &amp; flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of odyferouſe ſauour. &amp; certayne tymes it is good to be vſed a lytell of ſome perfume
<pb facs="tcp:16817:54"/> to ſtande in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mydle of the chamber. And in any wyſe lette not many men, and ſpecyally women be togyther at one tyme in the cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, not onely for bablynge, but ſpecially for theyr brethes. And the kepers ſhulde ſe at all tymes that the ſycke perſons drynke be pure, freſſhe &amp; ſtale, and that it be a lytell warmed, turned out of the colde. Yf the ſycke man wex ſycker and ſycker, that there is lykle hope of a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendment but ſygnes of deth, than no man oughte to moue to hym any worldly matters or buſynes: but to ſpeke of ghoſtly and godly matters. And to rede the paſſyon of cryſte. &amp; to ſay the pſalmes of the paſſyon, and to hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a croſſe or a pyctour of the paſſyon of cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes of the ſycke perſon. And let not the kepers forget to gyue the ſycke man in ſuche agony warme drynke with a ſpone, and a ſponefull of a cawdell or a coleſſe. And than lette euery man do indeuer hym ſelfe to prayer, that the ſycke ꝑſon may fynyſſhe his lyfe Catholyckely in the fayth of Ieſu cryſte And ſo departe out of this myſerable world. I do beſeche the Father, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone, and the holy ghoſt thorow the meryte of Ieſu cryſtes paſſyon, that I and all Creatures lyuynge may do. AMEN.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:55"/>
            <head>¶ Imprynted by me Robert wyer / dwellynge in ſeynt Martyns paryſſhe beſyde charynge Croſſe, at the ſygne of ſeynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſte.</head>
            <p>For Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gowghe, Cum priuilegio regali. Ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer (McKerrow 68): "St. John the Evangelist with eagle"</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:56"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16817:56"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
